<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A warning to take heede of Fovvlers psalter, giuen by Th. Sampson</title>
            <author>Sampson, Thomas, 1517?-1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102972</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838731</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838731</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3119</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11432)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3119)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1153:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A warning to take heede of Fovvlers psalter, giuen by Th. Sampson</title>
                  <author>Sampson, Thomas, 1517?-1589.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>111, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Vautrollier, for George Bishoppe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1578.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fowler, John, 1537-1579 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3119:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WARNING TO TAKE HEEDE OF FOVVLERS PSALTER, giuen by Th. Sampſon.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>ANCHORA SPEI</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Thomas Vautrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, for George Bishoppe. 1578.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3119:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3119:2"/>
            <head>TO MY VERY GODLY LOVING FREND, AND BROTHER, M. ROBERT ASKE GOLDSMITH, AND ONE of the Bridgemaiſters, of the Citie of London.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV did ſende of late vnto me, at one time (as you knovve) tvvo bookes, vvhich the
<hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaniſtes</hi> had ſent into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: the one vvas a <hi>Primer,</hi> the other a
<hi>Pſalter.</hi> The Primer is in latin, and is as I thinke, but a nevve burnishing of their old popish pelfe. I did not peruſe it, neither do I entende to beſtovv any labour thereabout. For manye yeares are paſſed, ſithence I did leaue my Primer, neither haue I any pleaſure novve to looke vppon thoſe pudles of poperie, in vvhich I vvas plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3119:3"/> in the dayes of my youth, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal.</hi> 25.</note> I do rather vvith the Pſalmiſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly praye the Lorde not to remember the faultes and ignoraunces of my youth, but according to his ovvne kindnes and for his goodnes ſake to forgiue me. It is beſides all this novv become a tickle peice of vvorke <hi>(M. Robert)</hi> to medle vvith Primers: vvill you knovv vvhy? The olde Primers are of late greatly diſgraced by pope <hi>Pius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſt. Pij v.</note> For he ſayeth, that they vvere filled vvith ſuperſtitious errours, and ſayth: that many forged prayers vvere thruſt into them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der falſe and feyned names of Sainctes. He calleth alſo all the pardons graunted in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and printed in their rubrikes into doubte. Thus doth this Pope dashe the deuotion of papiſtes. Therefore lette olde papiſtes looke vvell vvhat Primers they vſe, and take heede vvhich of them they doe truſt, leaſt they do not onely loſe their labour, but fall into the diſpleaſure of the Pope. And by the doinges of late Popes they maye ſee hovv vnſauery and vnſafe the doings of former
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3119:3"/> Popes are, for that vvhich one allovveth, an other diſallovveth, one promiſeth, an other denyeth. Therefore I thought good novv to leaue both them, &amp; their Primer. And becauſe the Pſalter ſeemed to be ſome ſtraunge noueltie, vvith vvhich the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours thought to make ſome freashe melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, I did take this their Pſalter into my hande: I did but touch the ſtringes thereof, to taſte vvhat ſounde it did giue: but I did not finde that in it, vvhich the name ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to promiſe, rather I finde in it vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery diſcorde, ſtringes falſe, and out of tune, &amp; other ſuch iarres, as by peruſing this litle pamphlet you may perceaue. VVhich I doe not ſend to you (my good brother) as though I thought that you either delighted in ſuch inſtruments as is that popishe Pſalter, or that you needed my helpe to dravv you from the delighte or dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of ſuch trumpery, in vvhich Papiſts do take their pleaſure. God hath by his grace ſeparated you farre from that ſecte, and brought you into his ovvne ſchoole, vvhere you may, &amp; do, vvith ioye,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3119:4"/> heare, learne, and taſte of the ſvveetnes of the Lorde, and haue the ſonges of life, and ſaluation, praiſe the Lorde for it. And pray him to holde you euer in this vvaye of life, that you may alvvayes haue your harte, and eare open, and vvholly ſette to heare the voice of Ieſus: and alſo cloſed, shutte and fully turned from thoſe falſe flatteringe, and entiſing, <hi>Syrene,</hi> popishe voices: vnto vvhich vvho ſo hearckneth pearisheth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediles. Novve though you neede not my labour herein taken, yet in recompence of your freindly and kinde remembring of me vvith ſuch nevves as do come to your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, I haue thought good to ſend you this vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten paper, to remaine vvith you as a token of my good vvill tovvardes you. And if your ſonne <hi>Iohn Aske,</hi> of vvhoſe vvell doinge in God, I haue ſome care vvith you, may be admonished by it to learne euen in his youth to bevvare of ſuch Popishe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, as is made in that Popishe <hi>Pſalter,</hi> &amp; to giue heede to the truth of Ieſus Chriſt, the only true doctrine of our life and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3119:4"/> I shalbe gladde, and reioyce to ſee him enryched vvith that fayth vvhich dvvelled in <hi>Gillian</hi> his naturall mother, doth dvvel in you his natural father novv, and ſo I hope shall vnto the ende. That in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of true vnderſtanding vvhich doth giue life in God, I vvishe to you and all yours, vvishe you the ſame to me and mine. Leceſter the
<hi>10.</hi> of October. <hi>1577.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>LAME Tho. Sampſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3119:5"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.</bibl>
               <p>Be fulfilled with the ſpirite, ſpeakinge vnto your ſelues in Pſalmes, and hymnes, &amp; ſpirituall ſonges, ſinging and making melodie to the Lorde in your hartes, giuing thankes alwayes for all thinges vnto God, euen the Father, in the name of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3119:5"/>
            <head>A WARNING TO TAKE HEEDE OF FOW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LERS PSALTER, GIVEN By Tho. Sampſon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath ben alwayes the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſuch as do departe from the trueth and faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus onely, and do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them ſelues to the errour, and vntruth of their owne choyſe, and are ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led therein, their manner hath ben, and is (I ſay) to inuente and deuiſe ſuch proper thinges as maye ſerue to induce other men to like of that which they doe, and by litle and litle to draw them to become like to them ſelues. And to this ende they doe vſe to paint their owne foule doinges with faire coulours: for they thinke if they ſhoulde at the firſt openly ſhowe that groſenes which is in their errour, they ſhoulde driue all men from them rather then allure any to them. And therfore they do make a choiſe of goodly wordes, and do ſet the ſame as cloſely as they can vpon their errour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they woulde by a ſhewe of that which is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3119:6"/> good, deceaue men the more readily, and draw them to their euill. So many olde Heretiques did in their hereſie retaine the name of Ieſus Chriſt, and vnder that moſt holy name they did hyde all their poyſon. They did ſpeake ſome good thinges, and cited alſo ſome ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of holy Scripture, vnder theſe good co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers to conueye their errours into the mindes of men. Likewiſe do the Papiſts now. They haue and hold for the couer of their filthes and abhominacions the names of God, of Chriſt, of Ieſus, of the Church, of the ſpirit, of truth, of Catholike, and what not? But all theſe they do vſe, but as a ſconſe to deceaue, and vnder theſe faire titles to drawe ſimple ſoules into their filth. They haue heretofore foughte for them ſelues in this lande with fire and ſworde feircely: but when that tyrannie was, as now it is, ouerturned, through Gods great mercy towardes vs, bleſſed be his name for it, by the moſt mercyfull and milde gouernement of our gratious ſoueraine <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> whoſe life amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs &amp; reigne ouer vs, God almighty proſper and prolonge: They ſoughte a while to holde &amp; maintaine their owne with bookes and writinges full of forgeries and of furiouſe ſpeaches, threates, &amp; curſed ſpeakinges. They haue alſo had their practiſes to recouer againe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3119:6"/> into their hands that gouernment which once they had, and now they haue loſte. In which deſire they haue ben, and are, as deſperately ſet, as any cruell tyraunte euer was, or can be. And though our good God hetherto hath of his moſt gratious goodnes diſappointed them of all their purpoſes (bleſſed be his name for it) yet they do ſtill biggly breath foorth blood, and ſlaughters, and ceaſe not. For euen at this day, they do by libells and letters threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our ruine, and blowe foorth their owne triumphe. And herein they are ſo forewarde, that they do name the perſons which ſhalbe (they ſaye) their captaines. They aſſigne the time in which they ſhall reigne ouer vs: they ſhall floriſhe, we ſhall ſmoake, or elſe their ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender fayleth them, yea they do note the men almoſt by name whom they haue appointed to the ſlaughter, and thus they do blowe vp the trumpette of their triumphe, but before the victory thankes be to God. Surely we do not feare them at all, but we do feare God, whoſe iuſt wrath we do prouoke, by our vnholy hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his moſt holy Goſpel. This, this is it, that doth moſt feare vs, for by this we know, that we do deſerue that he ſhoulde once againe ſcourge vs with the whippes of theſe Popiſh Philiſtines. But we do pray him, that he will
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3119:7"/> haue mercy on vs, euen for his owne goodnes ſake. For he is kinde, mercyfull, and ſlowe to wrath, yea he ſayth of him ſelfe. <hi>Iſai 27. <hi>Anger is not in me.</hi>
               </hi> May it pleaſe him therefore to giue vs the grace to be at peace, &amp; at one with him, we care not then, though all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes in the worlde, and all the Deuills in hell, do ſette them ſelues againſt vs. Whileſt they fume &amp; freatte at vs, we learne to beleeue that goodnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord which for our comfort he doth laye foorth, <hi>Iſai 48.</hi> where he ſayth: <hi>For my names ſake I will differ my wrath, &amp; for my praiſe I wil reſtraine it from thee, that I cutte thee not of, for mine owne ſake, will I do it.</hi> And we humbly pray as they did <hi>Ier. <hi>14. VVe acknowledge o Lorde our wickednes and the iniquities of our fathers, for we haue ſinned againſt thee: Doe not abhorre vs for thy names ſake: caſt not downe the throne of thy glory: remember, and breake not thy couenaunt with vs.</hi>
               </hi> And to this alſo we truſt, that he will haue an eye now, as euer he hath had, to his enemies, and cutte them ſhorte of their purpoſe, according to his owne good pleaſure, that they do not triumphe ouer him: &amp; ſo we know that God, as he is able, ſo he wil deale againſt them for vs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſai</hi> 2.</note> He doth bid vs not to feare man whoſe breath is in his noſtrells.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3119:7"/> For wherein is he to be eſteemed?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi>
10.</note> He biddeth vs not to feare them, which can but kill the body, but to feare him, who when he hath kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the bodie, hath power to caſt the ſoule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euerlaſting fire. Notwithſtanding all the bigge &amp; braue bragges which Papiſts make, it ſeemeth that all thinges as yet do not come about, to ſerue the turne ſo roundly as they woulde, and therefore in the meane time they do content them ſelues, to take a lower courſe, and will by cullor of prayer, creepe into our boſomes.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> But the Apoſtle ſayeth that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill can turne him ſelfe into the faſhion of an Angell of lighte: And therefore it is no great thinge though his miniſters tranſforme them ſelues as though they were the miniſters of righteouſnes, but their ende ſhalbe according to their workes. By libells at Oxford, and bulls from Rome, they breath out the furye of their conceaued malice, and ſodenly they chaunge their mode, into their kind of prayer. They do now herein, as their kinge the Pope hath done hertofore againſt vs. The laſt Pope <hi>Pius</hi> thundred out a bull of his curriſh cenſure againſt our good <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> to turne her out of her royall ſtate, and life, and after that he ſent into England cloſely a meſſenger whoſe name (as Doctor <hi>Saunders</hi> telleth vs)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3119:8"/> is <hi>Nicolas Morton,</hi> by office a prieſt, a meete officer for ſuch a Pope &amp; purpoſe. This man was ſente to follow that Popiſh bull, and he did it ſo freaſhly, that thereon did follow a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in the North partes of this lande. But God almightie quenched this fire in his moſt riche mercy. The rebells ranne their country, Pope
<hi>Pius</hi> by death is picked ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pearche: Our <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> doth ſtill holde her place, thankes be to God, &amp; reigneth in Godly quietnes: O Lord graunt that ſhe may longe ſo do. Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> that now is, ſeeing this roughe attempt of his predeceſſor haue ſo euil ſucces, chaungeth the courſe of his Popiſhe proceading, and hath nowe ſente by his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtes certain bulls into England, in which he promiſeth full remiſſion of ſinnes to them which after that diſſembled deuotion which he putteth downe, ſhal pray for the conuerſion of Englande (he ſayeth,) to the Catholicke fayth, but he doeth meane the peruertion of Englande from the true Chriſtian faith, into that filthe and falſehoode of the Romiſh error. Thus the Popes are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to fall from armes, fighting and curſing, to faire promiſes flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and praying. But I truſt Engliſh men for whoſe pleaſure the Pope wil ſeeme to haue brought foorth this bull, haue learned more
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3119:8"/> wiſedome in the Goſpell of God then now to be made calues by ſuch a Popiſh bull. In like manner our Louaniſtes, hauing ſpente (as it ſeemeth) the greateſt parte of their common ſhotte at vs, but in vaine (thankes be to God) beginne to allure vs to like of them by tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs to praye. But we haue already lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to praye of the beſt ſchoolemaiſter that euer was, is, or ſhalbe, euen of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. And therefore we haue no eare to hearken to theſe Popiſh bunglers and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of holy thinges. They haue to this ende publiſhed in prince of late a thing, which they call <hi>Ieſus Pſalter,</hi> and the author thereof, or <hi>Maſter Fowler,</hi> the printer therof doth tell vs:
<q>That there be three manner of Pſalters: the firſt is called Dauids Pſalter, which contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thriſe fifty Pſalmes: the ſecond <hi>(ſayth he)</hi> is called the Pſalter of our Lady, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teining thriſe fiftie Aues: the third is called the Pſalter of Ieſu, or the inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus, conteining fiftene prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall petitions, which tenne times repeated make alſo thriſe fiftie.</q>
            </p>
            <p>What meane theſe men ſo farre to forgette them ſelues that they do now commend to the Reader but theſe three manner of Pſalters? Their forefathers haue ben more liberall to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3119:9"/> vs as ſhall forthwith appeare. The Pſalter of <hi>Dauid</hi> conteyning
<hi>150.</hi> Pſalmes we do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be deliuered to vs by the ſpirite of God for our comforte and inſtruction. For Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe teacheth vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marc.</hi> 12.</note> that <hi>Dauid</hi> in his Pſalmes doth ſpeake inſpired by the holy Ghoſt. And therfore with all humblenes of harte and reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, we do receaue the ſame as a booke of holy Scripture deliuered to vs as other bookes of the holy Scripture are, euen by God him ſelfe. We do not receaue it as a Pſalter giuen to vs by the Papiſtes: For it is no Pſalter of theirs, although it pleaſeth them nowe in the accompte of Pſalters, to matche it with theirs, to make vp their packe of Pſalters. But what are theſe other two Pſalters of which they tell vs? Who hath blowen them foorth into the world? Let them tell vs alſo why they do not adde to this nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Pſalters, thoſe which their forefathers haue heretofore publiſhed as Pſalters to the worlde in printe? Be they now aſhamed of them? ſo may they be of this. They printed at <hi>Parris a Primer anno 1554.</hi> in the <hi>160.</hi> leafe of that booke they do giue vs an other Pſalter which they do there call, <hi>The Pſalter of Sainct Hierome,</hi> and they do in their <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke</hi> there tell vs, for how many purpoſes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3119:9"/> good (if we will beleeue them) the ſame Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was printed. In the ſame booke alſo <hi>Fol. 125</hi> they tell vs howe <hi>S. Bernard</hi> was on a time in his prayers, and the deuil ſayd to him, I know that there be certaine verſes in the Pſalter, who that doth ſaye them dayly ſhall not peariſhe, for he ſhall haue knowledge of the daye that he ſhall dye, but the feinde (ſaye they) woulde not ſhewe them to <hi>S. Bernard.</hi> Then ſayd
<hi>S. Bernard,</hi> I ſhall ſaye dayly the whole Pſalter. The feinde conſidering that
<hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſhould do ſo much profit to labour ſo, he ſhewed him the verſes there following. This is their <hi>Rubricke</hi> in that place, in which might be noted many thinges, which now I paſſe ouer. As firſt, that the deuill is buſie to daſill men in prayer. Againe that this was a packe of verſes bounde together by the deuill him ſelfe: An handſome peice of worke be ye ſure. And thus he doth now buſie him ſelfe, by this newe founde
<hi>Pſalter</hi> to playe his olde pranckes. But why be not theſe verſes thus packed together called <hi>S. Bernard</hi> his <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> as well as his verſes? and why be they not ioyned together as one Pſalter, with that other Pſalter of <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> to increaſe the number of Pſalters? For ſo mighte our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts yeeld vnto vs more Pſalters then three.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3119:10"/> They maye know alſo if they will, how that ſame their ſeraphicall doctor
<hi>S. Bonauenture</hi> did moſt ſhamefully corrupte the moſt holy Pſalter of
<hi>Dauid,</hi> chaunging through the whole Pſalter the name <hi>of Lorde</hi> into
<hi>Ladye</hi> to turne his reader from the Lord God, whom the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> praiſed, and to whom he prayed, vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> as his ſouerain. The booke is in printe, and therefore I leaue it to the veiw of them who luſt to ſee ſuch cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte Popiſh blaſphemies. But how happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it now, that our Papiſtes do make no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of that Pſalter, to be a Pſalter? True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as full of filth and blaſphemy as it is, yet is it adorned by ſome of their forefathers in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie with this glorious title:
<q>The Pſalter of the Virgin Mary, compiled by the deuoute doctor Sainct Bonauenture.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> with papiſts hath two Pſalters, or elſe ſome of them doe lye: why doth not <hi>M. Fowler</hi> tel vs of them? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I thinke he is as much bounde to tell vs of the one, as of the other. But it may be that by aduiſe he doth omitte theſe pſalters, becauſe our papiſtes now be aſhamed of the filth, and corruption of their forefathers: I would there were ſo much grace in them. Truely if there were, they would neuer haue ſent foorth this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3119:10"/> new corruption of theirs. They do therefore but deale doubly with the reader, to tell him but of three pſalters, as if there were with them no more but three pſalters, wheras they haue ſo many. But they woulde faine make a waye for this their new pſalter, therefore they ſuppreſſe the number and naminge of others. They tell vs that this is the
<hi>pſalter of Ieſu,</hi> good wordes. But why call they it a <hi>pſalter?</hi> There are ſome of their good maiſters in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,<note place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which do tell vs that a <hi>pſalter</hi> is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of tenne ſtringes, and theſe men do now tell vs that this their pſalter hath <hi>150.</hi> ſtringes, I meane <hi>petitions:</hi> therefore it is ſome new kinde of inſtrument deuiſed by their owne idle and corrupt braines. Their ſaide maiſters teach vs, that the pſalter, that is the inſtrument, which hath tenne ſtringes, doth ſignifie the tenne commaundements. And will <hi>M. Fowler</hi> tell vs on his credite, that this his new pſalter doth ſignifie the ten commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? If he do ſo tell vs, we ſhalbe able I hope to proue that this his pſalter, is but a counterfaite and falſe ſigne. More their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters do teache vs, that an <hi>hymne</hi> doth thus differ from a
<hi>pſalme.</hi> For an <hi>hymne</hi> (ſay they) is that ſonge which is ſonge with the naturall voice: but a <hi>Pſalme</hi> is that which is played
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3119:11"/> vpon an inſtrument. Now ſithence it is their pleaſure to giue vs a
<hi>pſalter,</hi> they will I thinke aſſigne ſome inſtrument wherevpon the
<hi>pſalmes</hi> of this <hi>pſalter</hi> maye be played. And ſo they do ful deuoutly forſooth. For they do aſſigne to them which ſhall ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle this their pſalter, to playe the ſame vpon their <hi>Tenne fingers.</hi> A proper inſtrument and ſoundeth as ſweetly, as when an Ape layeth his fore hands croſſe one vpon an other, and is taught to ſweare by his owne tenne bones, full ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kiſſing his proper pawes. This verely is but apes playe. But how aptly or vnaptly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it is to be called a pſalter, all is made vp by adding vnto the pſalter the name of Ieſu: for they call it the <hi>pſalter of Ieſu.</hi> The name of Ieſu hath in it an heauenly and glorious ſweetnes, when it is rightly looked into. For he that doth know him ſelfe to be a ſinner, and that he is to receaue the rewarde of ſinne, that is death and damnation by the moſt iuſte iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God: When this man with a trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and troubled ſpirite doth looke about quaking for feare, and hungry of helpe, and findeth that Ieſus is the true and only Ieſus, that it is he that ſaueth his people from their ſinnes, and therefore is euen the ſame in deede which his name noteth, that is a Sauiour:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3119:11"/> This poore ſoule reioyſeth with ioye vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable, becauſe he hath founde a <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in him ſelfe a taſte of that kingdome of God which is righteouſnes, ioye and peace in the holy Ghoſt. If <hi>M. Fowler</hi> did minde to teach his reader to vnderſtand what the name of Ieſus doth meane, he would I thinke haue told him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thing which the Angel did tell <hi>Ioſeph: Thou shalt cal his name Ieſus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt</note> 
               <hi>for he shall ſaue his people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſinnes.</hi> Where we learne that the name of <hi>Ieſus</hi> doth ſignifie a <hi>Sauiour:</hi> and Ieſus is he called becauſe it is he that doth ſaue his people from their ſinnes. And this ſauinge health hath ſuche a ſweete taſte in it, that it maketh the Virgin <hi>Marie, Simeon,</hi> and all other well taughte children of God, which do rightely taſte of this ſaluation, to reioyce in God their ſauiour. <hi>M. Fowler</hi> mighte alſo haue tolde vs out of <hi>Bernard</hi> that Ieſus is honey in the mouth,<note place="margin">Ber. in Serm. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> and melodie in the eare, and myrthe in the harte. And alſo that the name of Ieſus, is lighte, it is meate, it is medecine. For Ieſus is lighte to them which ſitte in darknes, he is meate to them which do hunger, and thriſt after righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſaluation: he filleth the hungry with good thinges: he is a medecine and a playſter of life for the ſicke ſoule and broken harte. Yea
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3119:12"/> if all theſe had miſliked him, he mighte haue tolde vs yet,<note place="margin">Ri. de ſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ict. ex Io.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath.</note> that one of his owne elders ſayth, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Ieſus is a ſweete name, a name full of delighte, a name comforting a ſinner, a name of good hope, and that this man thus ſpeaking of this name <hi>Ieſus,</hi> bruſteth foorth into prayer, as it ſhoulde ſeeme feeling ſome excellent ſweetnes in that name, and ſayth, <hi>O Ieſus be vnto me a Ieſus,</hi> that is, O Sauiour, be vnto me a ſauiour, or O ſauiour ſaue me. All theſe thinges <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth paſſe ouer, and giueth vs as he ſayth a <hi>pſalter of Ieſus,</hi> in which he doth teach vs ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to name the name of Ieſus. But it is a matter of vnderſtanding, ſence and feeling truely to ſpeake of Ieſus, it is not a matter of fidling with tenne fingers as <hi>M. Fowler</hi> teacheth. They which haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of Ieſus do know this beſt. This is not had nor feelt by looking on the letters, nor ſpelling of the name of Ieſus by ſillables, nor yet by bare pronouncing the name Ieſu. The old heretikes called <hi>Marcoſij</hi> made them ſelues much adoe about this name and the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thereof, yea and curiouſly deuiſed on ſome nomber which mighte be noted by the letters of this name as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> doth write. And notably doth this auncient writer ſaye to them all as in one:<note place="margin">Epiph. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra her. lib. <hi>1.</hi> to .
<hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vocem enim ſolum habes, virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3119:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> vero ipſius ignoras:</hi> that is, thou haſt onely the worde or voice, but the vertue or power thereof thou doeſt not know. It is one thing to pronounce the worde, and an other to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and feele the vertue and power noted by that word. This, this giueth life and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſpeake of Ieſus with vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding and ſenſe of that life and ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which Ieſus doth giue, is ſuch a thing as the holy Ghoſt doth worke in the elect alone, whereof the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſayeth <hi>1. Cor. 12.</hi> No man can ſaye that Ieſus is the Lorde, but by the holy Ghoſt. If we ſaye the Lord Ieſus truely, we are taught ſo to do by the holy Ghoſt, for it onely doth frame our tongues to make a true confeſſion of the Lord Ieſus, and of the ſaluation which by faith we do feele in our hartes that we haue by him: It teacheth vs to ſpeake of Ieſus not in bare ſpeache alone, but waying what we ſay, as
<hi>Hierom</hi> noteth in theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ioel.</note> 
               <hi>Tamen hoc ipſum dicere non ſermone ſed affectu cordis eſt ponderandum,</hi> that is, this ſaying is to be wayed with, and in affection of harte, not in, or with bare ſpeach. Otherwiſe many haue vſed this name Ieſus, and pronounced it, but euill, and to their owne hurte.<note place="margin">Act.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> We do reade of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine vagabounde coniurers which tooke in hande to name ouer them that had euill ſpirits
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3119:13"/> the name of the Lord Ieſus, ſaying: We do adiure you by Ieſus whom
<hi>Paule</hi> preacheth. They abuſed the name of Ieſus, they did not vnderſtande the vertue and power of Ieſus. Though they did pronounce the word Ieſus, yet had they not faith in Ieſus nor feeling of his power and ſauing health. They ſpake not of Ieſus by the holy Ghoſt, and in true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and they did ſpeede thereafter: For the euill ſpirite aunſwered them: Ieſus I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and <hi>Paule</hi> I know, but who are ye? Thus were theſe coniurers driuen awaye, beaten and wounded euen by the euill ſpirite, whom they thought to haue driuen awaye by pronouncing the name Ieſus. You maye ſee that coniurers, and the deuill him ſelfe can name and pronounce the name of Ieſus, and yet are no whitte the better for ſo doing. It is not therefore the bare pronouncinge of the name, that doth profit at all, as by this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is to be ſeene.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 13.</note> We do alſo reade of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine ſorcerer that made him ſelfe ſo boulde of this name Ieſus, that he called him ſelfe <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſus</hi> as though he were the very man of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And yet did this wretched man withſtand ſo much as he coulde the doctrine of Ieſus preached by <hi>Paule,</hi> and ſought to turne others from the faith, and labored to peruerte the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3119:13"/> ſtraight waye of the Lorde.<note place="margin">Math<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> We are by Ieſus Chriſt him ſelfe forwarned to take heede of ſuch as ſhall abuſe and counterfeit his name to deceaue and ſeduce vs, beleeue them not ſayth Chriſt. Suche a company of counterfeits are in Poperie. For in it they haue their brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoodes of Ieſus, their feaſtes of the name of Ieſus, their pardons of Ieſus, their Maſſe of the ſame, mattens howres and euen ſong of it. And of late dayes the Papiſts haue hatched and brought foorth a ſwarme of ſuch vermine as call themſelues <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> whoſe trauell is like to that of <hi>Barieſu,</hi> that is, to peruerte the right wayes of the Lorde Ieſus, to turne men from the true vnderſtanding of the vertue and power of Ieſus. To this purpoſe be they ſent foorth to carrye men from hearckening to the Goſpell of Ieſus, and from beleeuing truly in Ieſus, and yet they be called
<hi>Ieſuites,</hi> vnder this faire name to worke their feate, that is to ſeduce men and leade them from Ieſus. They are enemies to Ieſus, to his doctrine, power, &amp; ſauing health, as both by their name, doing and doctrine is proued at large, by that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned writer of our age
<hi>Martin Kemnitius.</hi> And euen ſo to their new found pſalter, is the name of Ieſu by them added, but as a ſnare whereby the pſalter maker woulde drawe his reader
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3119:14"/> from the truth of Ieſu into the puddle of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie. It may be maruailed greatly that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes dare thus boldly and impudently abuſe the name of Ieſus, the name of our bleſſed God and Sauiour. Haue they no conſcience of breaking Gods commaundement? <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lorde thy God in vaine, for the Lorde will not holde him giltles that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his name in vaine.</hi> Though now they do not feare to committe the faulte, yet ſhall they not eſcape but by a true verdicte be founde guilty of it before God. For to take his name, to confirme a falſhoode, is to take his name in vaine, and to breake his commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But thus do they now take the name of the Lorde Ieſus, therefore lette Papiſtes holde vp their handes and aunſwere guiltie, or not guiltie? if they pleade, not guiltie, they ſhall abide the triall before God by his lawe, and then they wilbe founde guiltie. I know it will grieue them to be thus charged, but if any of them do thinke them ſelues to be ouercharged here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, lette them tell vs truely who made them ſo bolde to applie the holy name of Ieſus to their owne deuiſes, to their Maſſes, pardons, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhoodes and ſuch trumperie, or to call their ſectaries
<hi>Ieſuites,</hi> or to call this their new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, the pſalter of Ieſu? did Ieſus Chriſt euer
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3119:14"/> giue them commiſſion thus to vſe his name? or did he euer make this pſalter? Lette them ſhew this by the holy Scriptures. If he did not, then lette them tell vs if any of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles or diſciples did make this pſalter, or did deliuer this pſalter to vs, and did tell vs on their creadite that it was the pſalter of Ieſus? If neither Chriſt Ieſus him ſelfe nor any of his Apoſtles, nor diſciples did deliuer this pſalter to vs, from whom then did it come? who did make it? who can aſſure vs that it is as they ſaye, the
<hi>pſalter of Ieſu?</hi> Who was ſo bolde with the name of the Lord Ieſus, to put it to this pſalter as though it were made by Ieſus? We know that there haue ben ſome olde deceauers which haue publiſhed their owne forgeries in the name of Ieſus, as there haue bene alſo manye double dealers which haue foyſted out their falſhoodes vnder the name of good men which haue bene of greate creadite in the Church of God. Surely our Papiſtes coulde not haue picked out a more glorious name then is this name of Ieſu, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which they mighte haue ſette foorth this their new founde pſalter. But this to do is to the authors thereof a thing moſt daungerous. For it maketh them guiltie of taking the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name of Ieſus in vaine, and ſheweth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3119:15"/> that they haue no deutifull regarde of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry due to the Lord Ieſus, and to his moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name. <hi>S. Paule</hi> intreating <hi>Philip. 2.</hi> how the Lorde of glorie Ieſus Chriſt did for our ſake, humble him ſelfe and became obediente to the death euen the death of the croſſe, ſayth alſo, that now God hath highly exalted him, and giuen him a name, aboue euery name, that at the name of <hi>Ieſu</hi> euery knee ſhoulde bowe of thinges in heauen and thinges in earth, and thinges vnder the earth, and that euery tonge ſhoulde confes that Ieſus Chriſt is the Lorde vnto the glorie of God the father. Thus doth the holy Apoſtle teach, that God hath giuen to Ieſus a name, a dignitie and power aboue all names, dignities, and powers. For all power in heauen and earth is giuen vnto him. He is ſo aboue all, that they all muſt bowe the knee at the name of Ieſus which as <hi>Hierom</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">Hieron. in epiſt. ad E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non ad genua corporis, ſed ad ſubiectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem mentis, &amp; inclinationem animae cordis<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequium pertinet:</hi> doth not pertaine to the bowinge of the knee of the bodie, but it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to the ſubiection of the mind, the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of the ſoule, and obedience of the harte, for all muſt obey him and be ſubiect to Ieſus, to the will, maieſtie &amp; power of Ieſus Chriſt. Sithence this glorie is due and to be giuen to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3119:15"/> our Lorde Ieſus and to his glorious name, howe dare Papiſtes be thus bolde to vſe and abuſe it, to filthie ſectes of their owne ſetting foorth, to brotherhoodes, to pardons, feaſtes, Maſſes, mattens, pſalters &amp; ſuch like thinges as they deuiſe them ſelues? vnder that moſt holy name to gette creadite to their falſhoodes and ſale to their marchaundiſe. Now we Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians do know by the doings and preachings of Ieſus, which are ſette foorth vnto vs by the moſt true witneſſes of him, that is by his holy Apoſtles and diſciples, we do by their witnes perceaue, that Ieſus made no ſuch brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoodes, feaſtes, Maſſes, mattens, howres, Euenſonges, pardons, no ſuch pſalters, for if he had, they woulde haue made ſome mention of them. Yea and by the comparing of that which they did truely write of Ieſu, with theſe forgeries of Papiſtes, we ſee the contrariety betwene them ſo greate, that their firſt moſt auncient and true writinge doth ſufficiently condemne theſe popiſh nouelties, and this new pſalter as a noueltie of falſhoode and errour. I call it a noueltie as it is. If Papiſtes will diſproue me, then lette them ſhow what A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, what auncient apoſtolique man, what approued auncient catholique doctor, what auncient generall councell hath commended
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3119:16"/> vnto vs this pſalter as <hi>the Pſalter of Ieſu?</hi> If any, ſhewe vs: but if none, then is it a nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie deuiſed either by that ſecte of <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> or els it may be that <hi>Fowler</hi> now wanting worke to occupie his preſſe (for his olde maiſters which were wont to ſette him on worke haue ſpente their ſtoare, and do not occupie him ſo freaſhely as they haue done and him ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth) hath deuiſed with ſome of his brethren how to make this pſalter, and ſo it maye be called <hi>Fowlers pſalter,</hi> but not <hi>the pſalter of Ieſus.</hi> He doth adorne his worke with this braue title: <hi>Certaine deuoute and Godly peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, commonly called Ieſus pſalter.</hi> What de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion and godlynes is in them ſhall hereafter appeare. But lette <hi>M. Fowler</hi> tell vs when did this <hi>common callinge</hi> beginne? I ſaye when did it beginne? and among whom? It muſt haue a large compaſſe that is <hi>common.</hi> Is it ynough to make it common becauſe now the Papiſtes doe call it common? or becauſe <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth by his printe call it common? Truely this is but a ſtraighte, narrow and ſhorte common: but euen ſuch a common is this as is their
<hi>catholiciſme.</hi> In this their pſalter they do as truely name <hi>common,</hi> as they do in the reſt of their religion name <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique:</hi> for there is no truth in either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.

<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3119:16"/> Neither is this <hi>pſalter</hi> ſo commonly called, nor their religion
<hi>Catholique,</hi> but onely ſo called by them ſelues. It ſeemeth alſo that the worke of this pſalter did fall out ſhorter, then <hi>M. Fowler</hi> thought it would, and therefore he hath filled vp aboue three ſcore leaues of his booke as in one of his copies is to be ſeene, though it be lefte out in the leſſer booke, with a certaine new deuiſed Imagerie, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſithence wordes fayled him, he might yet fill vp his booke with ſome thing to feede the eyes of his ſimple reader, that is with a new ſtampe of Imagerie. This his workemanſhippe of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magerie he doth adorne with this title: <hi>Godly contemplations for the vnlearned.</hi> He doth alſo for confirmation of this his worke adde a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence out of <hi>Baſill</hi> which he turneth into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh meeter, &amp; yet cannot this his whole worke of Imagerie be warranted by that ſentence of <hi>Baſill.</hi> For it ſpeaketh of ſuch Imagerie one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as is reported vnto vs by hiſtorie. But there are among the images made by <hi>M. Fowler</hi> ſome, whereof we haue no reports by hiſtorie. In what hiſtorie doth he reade, that the Lorde God almightie which made both heauen and earth, did in the creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them ſhew him ſelfe in the likenes of an aged perſon with a crowne vpon his heade? It was wont to be among
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3119:17"/> popiſh painters a triple &amp; Popelike crowne, but with <hi>M. Fovvler</hi> it is nowe but a ſingle crowne, not ſo much as a cloſe crowne, ſuch as kinges &amp; monarches do weare, but euen ſuch a one as it pleaſeth <hi>M. Fowler</hi> to put vpon his head. Who taught <hi>M. Fowler</hi> to be thus bold with the Lorde God, to make ſuch a baſe and earthlie image of his glorious and heauenlie Maieſty? Let vs looke for his aunſwere. In the meane ſeaſon we will be ſo bolde with <hi>M. Fowler</hi> &amp; his fellowe helpers to aske of them the ſame queſtion which is asked in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of <hi>Iſay <hi>40: To whome will yee liken God: or what ſimilitude will yee ſet vp vnto him. And againe, to whom wil yee liken me? that I should be like vnto him, ſayth the holy one?</hi>
               </hi> Aunſwere <hi>M. Fowler,</hi> aunſwere to theſe queſtions, and lette vs heare how you can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende this your bold doing, and this your like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the immortall God to a mortall &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible man. Let him ſhewe vs alſo in what hiſtory he findeth that there was before Chriſt on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> top of the mountaine on which he praied, a Chalice with a litle round hoſt or cake in it, holden (as he doth graue it) in the hand of an Angell. And where did he reade that Chriſt Ieſus did deſcende into hell corporally with a long ſtaffe in his hande, hauing a croſſe and a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3119:17"/> banner cloth in the top of it, &amp; did there drawe ſoules by the handes out of hell, by a payre of ſtayres at a great gate of hewen ſtone, as his imagery ſheweth: let not <hi>M. Fowler</hi> now ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill &amp; ſay that I do deny an article of our chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith. For I doe firmely beleue, that Article, <hi>he deſcended into hell:</hi> but I do not beleue that this image which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> hath graued, doth truely ſet foorth the trueth of the deſcending of Chriſt into hell. Let <hi>M. Fowler</hi> therefore ſhewe by what true hiſtorie, he can proue this his image and all the partes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Likewiſe let him ſhewe vs what hiſtorie it is that reporteth vnto vs the trueth of that his image, in which he graueth howe the virgine <hi>Mary</hi> was perſonally or bodily aſſumpted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen, by the handes of Angells, a great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of people kneeling by &amp; worſhipping. And laſt of all let him tel vs in what hiſtory he findeth the reporte of the next followinge i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. That is, how the virgine
<hi>Mary</hi> beinge in heauen was crowned by two men, the one ſittinge vppon the one ſide, and the other man ſittinge on the other ſide, of her: Let vs know what theſe two me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were? what be their names? &amp; when the ſolemnitie of this coronation was kept? And let him alſo tell vs by what catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſence this coronation is proued by that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3119:18"/> place of holie Scripture which he doth there cite <hi>Cantic. 4:</hi> to vnderproppe this his image? we know the place of holy Scripture, but we know not where this catholike ſenſe which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth gather thereon, where (I ſay) the vnderſtanding of that place, to ſerue the coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> was coyned. There are none of all his images, but that they haue <hi>M. Fowlers</hi> approbation by coatinge ſome chapters of ſome booke of the holy bible. But a number of them ſtande there but to fill vppe a place to make a ſhew of ſome thinge and ſay nothing. Thus he is bolde with naminge the bookes of the holy bible, to ſhore vp his ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, which can not ſtande by them. With ſuch images, which haue neither hiſtorie nor wryter of credite to reporte them, it pleaſeth <hi>M. Fowler</hi> for want of better matter to fill vp his booke, to pleaſe and feede the eyes of his ſimple reader which is not done accordinge to that rule which him ſelfe citeth out of
<hi>Baſill.</hi> But lette vs leaue <hi>M. Fowler</hi> with his new i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined imagery to him ſelfe, &amp; lette me aſke this. Dare <hi>Fowler,</hi> or any of his fellowes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe a pſalter, and father the ſame vppon the lord Ieſus as though he were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> author there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? Surely this his boldenes draweth nigh to blaſphemie and very nigh to the ſinne againſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3119:18"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt: for (as I ſaid before) it is a plain breaking of Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement. He taketh the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord Ieſus in vaine. And he alſo ſpeaketh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord Ieſus an vntrueth againſt his owne conſcience &amp; knowledge, in calling it <hi>the pſalter of Ieſus</hi> as though Ieſus had made it. But it may be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>M. Fowler</hi> will ſay for him ſelfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he will not auow, that Ieſus made this Pſalter, or that it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pſalter of Ieſus. If he will not auowe, but deny his owne wordes, I am content herein, to take his denial, &amp; thinke that it is not as he tearmeth it, <hi>the Pſalter of Ieſus.</hi> And ſo I may well make my ſelfe the more bolde to deale with this Pſalter, and to touche the ſtringes thereof, to trie whether they be in tune or not. Yea if it were ſo in dede, that
<hi>Fowlers</hi> meaninge is not to ſette out this Pſalter, as though it were made by Ieſus Chriſt, why doth he call it <hi>the Pſalter of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus?</hi> I wil take mine aunſwere out of his own words. It is (ſaith he) <hi>the Pſalter of Ieſu,</hi> or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Inuocation of Ieſu. M. Fowler</hi> ſeemeth to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate this word <hi>Pſalter</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> following word
<hi>Inuocation.</hi> Then with <hi>M. Fowler,</hi> the word <hi>Pſalter</hi> is all one with that word which out of the Latine tongue we borrowe into our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe, and do tearme it
<hi>Inuocation,</hi> which in proper engliſh is, a calling vpon, ſo that this
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3119:19"/> 
               <hi>Pſalter of Ieſu,</hi> is as much to ſay in Engliſhe as the callinge vppon Ieſu. And this may be gathered to be his meaninge, becauſe that the name of
<hi>Ieſu</hi> is ſo often repeated in his Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But if <hi>M. Fowler</hi> will ſuffer his great maiſter <hi>Thomas</hi> to tell vs what a Pſalter is, and what it doth ſignifie as I haue cited out of him before, then can not (I trowe) this his interpretation of the worde Pſalter ſtande. But I am content to leaue him to trye this matter with his ſayed maiſter him ſelfe. The name of Ieſus is glorious, pretious &amp; of great power as I haue ſayd, and therefore none can name that name rightly but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt. Wherof it is alſo, that they which do rightly name the name of the Lord Ieſus, are taught to departe from iniquitie. If the meaninge of <hi>M. Fowler</hi> be to teache his ſimple reader to <hi>Inuocate</hi> or to call vppon the Lord Ieſus, he muſt do that he meaneth truly by the word of God, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely ground worke of <hi>Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And <hi>M. Fowler</hi> muſt firſt teach his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to beleue truely in the Lorde Ieſus before he can well inuocate or call vppon him. For the Apoſtle teacheth <hi>Ro. 10.</hi> that men doe call on him on whom they do beleue. They beleue that which they haue hearde by the worde preached, if there be no worde of God hearde,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3119:19"/> there is no true beliefe, if there be no true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife, there is no calling vppon, or to vſe his tearme, no <hi>Inuocation</hi> &amp; ſo no <hi>Pſalter.</hi> Nowe
<hi>Maiſter Fowler</hi> preacheth not the worde of God, nor the Goſpell of Ieſus, to warrant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs this his <hi>Pſalter,</hi> neither doth he in it teach vs truely to beleue in the Lorde Ieſus. But in this <hi>Pſalter</hi> he doth teach his reader to pronounce ſome thinges which are contrary to the worde of God, and againſt the trueth of Ieſus, as ſhall appeare by that handeling of this <hi>Pſalter</hi> which followeth. If then the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this
<hi>Pſalter</hi> doth not by <hi>Maiſter Fowler</hi> heare to beleue, he can not inuocate nor pray: For how ſhall they call on him on whom they doe not beleue? Chriſt our Sauiour and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter teacheth vs thus of prayer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 21</note> whatſoeuer ye ſhall aske in prayer, if ye beleue, ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it. And againe, whatſoeuer ye deſire when ye pray,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marke.</hi> 1</note> beleue that ye ſhall haue it and it ſhall be done to you. Thus doth our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maiſter teach vs to ioyne faith to our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and prayer to our faith. And his Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> inſtructing vs how to pray,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iacob.</hi> 1.</note> biddeth him that prayeth aske in faith and wauer not, for he that wauereth is like to a waue of the ſea toſt with the winde and carried away, neither let that man thinke that he ſhall obteyne any
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3119:20"/> thing of the Lord. As for this kinde of inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion which <hi>M. Fovvler</hi> teacheth in his Pſalter is to trayne his Reader onely to name <hi>Ieſus,</hi> but that is a thinge which manye haue done without faith, and a thinge vnprofitable as ye haue hearde. A moſt certeine and comfortable rule is giuen vs whereby we are to be ruled in prayer, that is: If we aske any thing of God according to his wil, it ſhal be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs as holy <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth
<hi>1. lo. 1.</hi> Now how God would haue vs to pray: Ieſus him ſelfe hath taught vs, not onely in that prayer which he did teach vs, and is therefore of him called <hi>the Lordes prayer,</hi> but alſo in thoſe precepts in which he doth commaund vs to aske of the father in his name, &amp; without doubting as you haue parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heard before. Theſe and other like to them, verely be the right rules of prayer taught in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God, by the rule of which we muſt frame all our prayer, if we will ſo pray that we may be heard and obteyne. For it is deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be weighed of vs, that Ieſus Chriſt doth couple our praying together bothe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faith as you haue heard, and alſo with our abiding in him &amp; the abyding of his worde in vs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>If ye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in me ſayth he, and my vvordes abide in you, aske vvhat ye vvill and it shall be don for you.</hi> If we will pray profitably, we muſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3119:20"/> abide in Chriſt, and his word in vs. But <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Fovvler</hi> giueth vs an <hi>inuocation</hi> or <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Ieſu,</hi> for which he hath no worde of Chriſt, and by which he draweth his reader &amp; follower from Chriſt &amp; from his word as ſhal appeare hereafter. There can be no profit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this <hi>Pſalter</hi> of <hi>Fovvler.</hi> The onely true &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable rules of praier (once again I ſay) are thoſe which are giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs by Ieſus Chriſt, his Apoſtles &amp; diſciples in the worde of God: he that ſhall giue vs any other rules of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er contrary to thoſe, is but a deceauer, what fayre worke ſoeuer he make in outwarde ſhew of them. They are therefore but filthes and forgeries, with which Papiſtes haue farced their olde Prymers, and called them prayers receiued by reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though they be bomba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with popiſh pardons in plenty. Nowe let vs try &amp; examine this Pſalter, which <hi>M. Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> calleth <hi>Ieſus Pſalter,</hi> by thoſe true rules of prayer which Ieſus Chriſt hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. The name of Ieſu is holy, ſweete, &amp; comfortable: but <hi>M. Fowler</hi> hath ioyned vnto it a Pſalter very vnſauery and hurtefull. True Chriſtians which haue right faith do not lightly receaue wicked things, they doe ſeparat right things from thoſe which are euill as the chriſtian em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> did write to certeine Biſhops.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3119:21"/> Let vs therfore ſeparate the addicions which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> in his Pſalter hath ioyned to the good name of Ieſu, that the chriſtian may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template that bleſſed name as it is by it ſelf, &amp; that things differing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it may be eſpied out &amp; refuſed. But before I do come to the petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> patcheth vp his pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſomewhat more muſt be ſpoken touchinge thoſe other Pſalters which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth ſo boldly publiſh and commend to the world. He telleth vs that there be three manner of Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, he might haue told vs of more Pſalters as I haue ſaid before. <hi>Dauids pſalter</hi> we know we read with comforte and thanke God for it: we do with humble hartes receaue it, with all the whole number of <hi>150.</hi> Pſalmes, which number <hi>M. Fowler</hi> diuideth into thriſe fiftie, to make a way into ſome miſtery belike of his other Pſalters. The ſeconde is (ſayth he) cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Pſalter of our Lady.</hi> Is it called ſo <hi>M. Fowler?</hi> by whom? or who hath giuen it that name? did your Lady make it? did ſhe ſo call it? If not ſhe, who then? We will not take thinges vppon your bare reporte <hi>M. Fowler.</hi> Tell vs therfore the author of this Pſalter as you doe of the firſt which is <hi>Dauids,</hi> elſe you wil make this your ſtuffe ſuſpected. You paſſe from the name to the matter of this Pſalter,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3119:21"/> and doe tell vs that this Pſalter of your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy containeth thriſe fifty Aues. I told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>M. Fowler</hi> did deuide the number of the Pſalmes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pſalter of <hi>Dauid</hi> into thriſe fiftie, to make thereby a way into ſome miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his other Pſalters. And nowe yee ſee, that his ſeconde Pſalter though it doth in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe reſemble that of <hi>Dauid,</hi> yet he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it to reſemble the ſame in the number of thriſe fifty, and in the tearme <hi>Pſalter.</hi> A proper peece of worke. But once againe I aske who hath tolde <hi>M. Fowler</hi> that his Ladie Pſalter contayneth the iuſt number of thriſe fiftie A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues? Truly I thinke there are more then thriſe fifty men and women in England &amp; elſe where yet plunged in poperie, which can not tell vs by iuſt accompt that thriſe fifty Aues do make their Lady Pſalter. And no maruell: for it is a very harde thing for an vnlearned perſon to know the perfection of that thing which hath ſo obſcure a beginninge as hathe this Ladie Pſalter. But lette it paſſe vpon the credite of <hi>M. Fowler,</hi> if any like vpon his credite to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it: yet may I aske why theſe Aues thus packed together are called a <hi>Pſalter?</hi> It is no inſtrument of tenne ſtringes therefore no Pſalter. But
<hi>Fowler</hi> teacheth his reader to ſaye it vppon his tenne fingers, what inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3119:22"/> call you that? ſurely theſe are but chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhe and a piſhe toyes. It is no inuocation, it is no prayer, for it hath no petition in it, as it is graunted by <hi>M. Fowler</hi> his greate frende <hi>M. Vaws,</hi> euen there where he maketh the moſt that he can of the <hi>Aue Maria:</hi> howe can it be then any inuocation? or howe can it be a Pſalter.
<hi>M. Fowler</hi> muſt take the payne to make this matter more playne to vs, in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhewe of trueth, or elſe we will tell him plainely that this his Pſalter muſt be turned ouer to him ſelfe, for his owne paſtime, to be played vppon his tenne fingers. For I do not elſe thinke that any man of good vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge will daunce after his pipe. But lette vs come to this his thirde Pſalter vnheard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this our age, that is, <hi>the Pſalter of Ieſu:</hi> which
<hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth ſay, doth containe <hi>fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene principall petitions, which tenne times repeated make alſo thriſe fiftie.</hi> Thus is the miſterie made vppe which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to vs, when in the accompt of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of <hi>Dauid,</hi> he did deuide the number of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into thriſe fiftie. And all this is but to ſhewe the reader that theſe Pſalters as <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth temper them do agree in name and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, though in nothing els. But we thinke not that this agreement in name &amp; number only,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3119:22"/> either can, or doth make this newe Pſalter of <hi>M. Fowlers</hi> a perfect Pſalter, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering how this Pſalter of <hi>M. Fowlers</hi> trimming doth dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from that ſound Pſalter of <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp; from the doctrine of God. <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth tell vs that in his <hi>Pſalter</hi> and <hi>Inuocation, the glorious name of Ieſu, is called vppon foure hundred and fifty tymes.</hi> Tell vs not how often, but how wel you doe call vpon this name moſt holy, &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in deede. For it is not in inuocation y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to pronounce the letters and ſyllables of the worde <hi>Ieſu,</hi> but we muſt looke into that name by faith and ſo by faith feede on the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, ſauing health, and power of Ieſu, that it may encorage vs to call vpon him in faith and ſure confidence, knowing that he and he only, yea he, and none other vnder heauen but he, is giuen to men by whome they muſt be ſaued. which thing <hi>S. Peter</hi> preacheth in that ſermon <hi>Act. 4.</hi> a part of which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth cite. If I ſhould find falt with his tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlation, he would ſay that I did but picke quarrells. But to the matter. If nothing at all be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to men wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they muſt be ſaued, then are all men da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned: but there is one and but onely one thing for all giuen, whereby men muſt be ſaued, &amp; that one thing, as <hi>Peter</hi> doth there tell vs, is the Lord Ieſus. Other name, power, or thing, there is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3119:23"/> none in which men muſt be ſaued, but that one onely name, vertue and power, the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. And if as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">De verb. Ap. ſerm. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> we muſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in this name, doubtles that is no ſaluation which is promiſed without this name. And therefore doth <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſay that there is
<hi>no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in any other, for among men there is giuen none other name vnder heauen wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we muſt be ſaued.</hi> This tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlation ſemeth to expreſſe the mynd and purpoſe of
<hi>S. Peter</hi> ſomewhat more plainly then that of <hi>M. Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> where he doth tranſlate, <hi>In the which it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth vs to be ſaued.</hi> What preaty thing it is that
<hi>M. Fowler</hi> would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uey vnder this terme <hi>behoueth</hi> I know not, and therfore I leaue it. But the minde of <hi>S. Peter</hi> is to teache vs, that Ieſus is that perſon by whom only and alone, the good pleaſure of God is to ſaue men, and by whom onely they muſt be ſaued, that ſhall be ſaued. To perceaue this, is not onely to name Ieſus, but to haue true vnderſtanding of, &amp; faith in Ieſus. Without this true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding &amp; faith to ſownd out, or to pronounce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Ieſus doth profit no more men now, then it did the old exorciſts and coniurers, yea, or the deuills which pronounced that name, or the olde hereticks which did alſo retaine that name in their hereſie, and pronounced it with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3119:23"/> their lippes. And therefore <hi>M. Fowler</hi> your aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of your reader to find ſuch commoditie by your <hi>Inuocation,</hi> which with you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth onely almoſt in the often and bare pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the name Ieſus, is not ſo ſure, as you woulde ſeeme to make it. You tell vs alſo that our ſauiour hath taught vs in the Goſpell of <hi>S. Iohn: that we should make our petitions in his name.</hi> In deede we doe heare our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus ſay in that holy Goſpell written by <hi>S. Iohn 14. chapter. VVhatſoeuer ye aske in my name that will I doe, that the father may be glorified in the ſonne: If ye aske any thing in my name, I will doe it.</hi> For to this, as to one ende, are true Chriſtians ordeined, <hi>that whatſoeuer</hi> (ſayth Chriſt) <hi>Ioan. 15. ye shall aske of the father in my name, he may giue it you:</hi> and againe, <hi>Ioan. 16. Verely verely I ſay vnto you, whatſoeuer ye shall aske the father in my name, he will giue it you.</hi> Theſe and the like precepts of prayer, and promiſes of obtaining our requeſts, we knowe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſonne of God our moſt gracious Lorde Ieſus hath made to vs, and in them we doe reſt. But what meaneth that which followeth in this Pſalter of <hi>M. Fowlers?</hi> in theſe words, <hi>which</hi> (Ieſus he doth meane)
<hi>is the Mediator of our ſaluation.</hi> It is true verely <hi>M. Fowler,</hi> that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3119:24"/> Ieſus is the onely alone Mediator meane and worker of our ſaluation, as the former ſaying of <hi>Peter</hi> doth teach. But <hi>M. Fowler</hi> this is not all that is in Ieſus. In theſe your wordes you doe leaue out a peece of the office and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus. And herein you doe followe ſome of your olde popiſh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who to finde out ſome place for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of their Sainctes, are bolde to ſpoyle Chriſt of one peece of his office, and to beſtowe it on Sainctes. For they ſaye that Chriſt is our Mediator of ſaluation, but thof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of interceſſion they do commit to ſaincts, who they ſay do make interceſſion for vs. But we doe learne in the holy Scriptures, that as Ieſus Chriſt alone is the Mediator of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, by whome we are ſaued: ſo is he our Mediator of interceſſion, for it is he which maketh interceſſion for vs. That ſame very place which <hi>M. Fovvler</hi> citeth out of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> in which he ſayth that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour doth ſay that we ſhould make our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his name, teacheth that Ieſus is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator alſo of interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For to make our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions in his name, is to acknowledge him to be our interceſſor.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>S. Paule</hi> likewiſe ſpeaking of the moſt happy ſtate, in which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful doe ſtand before God by the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption which they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3119:24"/> haue by Chriſt Ieſus, ſayeth amonge other things: <hi>It is God that iuſtifieth, who shal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne. It is Chriſt which is deade, yea or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is riſen againe,</hi> he meaneth which iuſtifieth. And of Chriſt his office towards vs he continueth ſaying: <hi>who is alſo at the right hand of God and maketh interceſſion for vs.</hi> Here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Apoſtle teacheth vs ſo to looke to Ieſus Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may knowe that as it is he which died for vs, did riſe againe, &amp; aſcende, &amp; is at the right hande of God for our ſaluation, euen ſo he it is alſo, that maketh interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or requeſt for vs. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrues</hi> the <hi>7.</hi> chapter, the Apoſtle ſpeaking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting prieſthood of Chriſt ſaith: <hi>wherfore he is able perfectly to ſaue them that come vnto God by him, ſeing he liueth euer to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> He ſaith likewiſe afterward <hi>He. 9.</hi> That Chriſt is entred into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare now in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of God for vs. Again that bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> in his epiſtle teacheth vs <hi>1. Ioh. 2. If any man do ſin we haue an aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the father, Ieſus Chriſt the righteus &amp; he is the reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliation for our ſins.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle teacheth vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt Ieſus is our only &amp; ſufficient aduocate &amp; attonement with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office &amp; worke of interceſſion &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ioyned together in Chriſt Ieſus
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3119:25"/> alone.<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Epi. Ioan. tract. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> And here <hi>M. Fowler</hi> his frendes could haue tolde him that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> intreatinge v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this place of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> doth count it a thing antichriſtian, hereticall, and ſchiſmaticall, to aſſigne any other aduocate or interceſſor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene God and man but Ieſus Chriſt. But perhappes they woulde make deintie ſo to do, leaſt the chriſtian reader ſhould thereby be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coraged to accompt <hi>Fovvler</hi> and ſuch papiſts as he is, which do robbe Chriſt of this glorie of being our aduocate and interceſſor with the father, and do beſtow that office and honor v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their Sainctes, to accompt them (I ſay) to be antichriſtes, heretikes, &amp; ſchiſmatikes, as they are in deede. The chriſtian which can content him ſelfe with the doctrine and worde of God, is taught as you do heare, that Chriſt Ieſus is nowe at the right hande of God, and maketh requeſt for vs, that we muſt goe to God by him, who liueth to make interceſſion for vs, that he is our aduocate with the father, and ſo Chriſt him ſelfe ſayth <hi>Ioan. 14.</hi> of him ſelfe: <hi>I am the vvay, the trueth, &amp; the life: No man commeth to the father, but by me.</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence then we haue Ieſus the euerliuing, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, and moſt mercifull aduocate and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſor with the father, let vs giue vnto him the honor due to him with faithfull confeſſion
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3119:25"/> thereof, and thankes giuing therefore, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo do our ſelues as the Apoſtle doth exhort vs, <hi>Hebr. 4. Let vs therefore goe boldely</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>vnto the throne of grace, that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue mercy, and find grace to helpe in time of neede.</hi> Thus much touching this peece of legierdemain which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> vſeth euen at the entrey into his Pſalter to ſpoyle Ieſus Chriſt of his office, and glory of being our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſor and aduocate, to make place for his Pſalter which is patched vp, as ſhal hereafter appeare, with praying to Sainctes to make interceſſion for vs. By the ſworde of the ſpirit, which is the word of God, ſuch patches of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery are to be pared away, &amp; the chriſtians are to be left to their Ieſus Chriſt alone, both for ſaluation &amp; interceſſion. If it ſhall pleaſe God to make this poynt of our Chriſtian faith and religion well knowne, vnderſtanded, and the comfort thereof felt in the conſciences of men, they wil fall as faſt and thicke from popery to Chriſt his Goſpell, as bees doe flye out of the rayne to their hyues. But it ſhall be good to proceede in this Pſalter. The Reader may thinke that I do hange long in the beginning thereof, but <hi>M. Fowlers</hi> entry into it being ſo fowle, it is meete that the reader ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed thereof, to the ende he may be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3119:26"/> of it, &amp; deliuered (if it ſo be the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God) from ſticking or ſincking into ſo fowle a puddle with <hi>Fowler,</hi> as is this Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Let it be marcked then, that <hi>M. Fovvler</hi> doth giue vs a <hi>Pſalter of Ieſus</hi> (he ſayth) in which he taketh from Ieſus at the firſt daſhe a principall peece of his honor and office. Such ſacriledge <hi>Fowler</hi> and his fellowes can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and dare couer their villanie with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Ieſus. But this is but to fill vp the number of their ſinnes. Then
<hi>M. Fowler</hi> taketh paines to teach his reader, how he muſt ſay this pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and (ſayth he) <hi>he may ſay it vppon his tenne fingers,</hi> and why not vpon his tenne toes? He ſayth alſo that his ſcholler which will learne of him how to ſay this pſalter, muſt begin <hi>with deuout genuflection,</hi> or at the leaſt wiſe, with <hi>Inclination to Ieſu.
<hi>M. Fowler</hi>
               </hi> forgetteth him ſelfe (I trowe) for he will ſeeme to ſette out this Pſalter for the vnlearned, but the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned knowe not what theſe tearmes
<hi>genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection</hi> and <hi>inclination</hi> doe meane. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let <hi>Maiſter Fowler</hi> ſpeake Engliſh to his vnlearned ſchollers. After that he hath thus prepared his Reader to this Pſalter, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth the firſt petition and doth in it name the name of Ieſu thirtie tymes together, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to euery thryſe naminge of Ieſu, this
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3119:26"/> worde <hi>Mercie.</hi> If he meaneth to teache his Reader to praye the Lorde Ieſus to haue mercie on him, we doe agree with him in that good prayer, and ſo praye we. But if there be any myſterie in this often repeatinge of the worde or name <hi>Ieſu,</hi> it is a thing hidden from vs, ſo often to repeate that name with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further inſtruction. Is it
<hi>Maiſter Fovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> mynde to teache his Reader to thincke that this bare and often repeatinge of that name, and that in ſuch a iuſte number as is by him prefixed, is therefore an acceptable prayer, becauſe it is ſo often repeated onely? Surely that conceipte ſauoreth ſtrongely of that battologie, and lippe labour which Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt reiecteth. <hi>Matth.
6.</hi> I might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo note the ſtraungenes of the phraſe of that petition whiche he putteth downe in theſe wordes, where he ſpeaketh of ſinners. <hi>Turne</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>their vices into vertues:</hi> this is one in all his petitions. But it is but a ſtraunge tranſmutation that he asketh. It had bene more playne to haue ſayde, Turne ſinners from their vices to vertues, but to lette this paſſe. That ſauoreth ſtrongly of the Popes pumpe whiche followeth in theſe wordes: <hi>Haue mercye</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>on the ſoules in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorye for thy bytter paſſion I beſeech thee; and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3119:27"/> for thy glorious name Ieſu.</hi> It ſhal not be amiſſe now to ſay ſomwhat to the reader of this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie which hath beene and is the common pickepurſe, for the Pope and his chaplaines the maſſinge prieſtes. I knowe it will anger the papiſtes to heare of this, for it toucheth their free holde (as the common ſayinge is.) But I will lay before the reader, this popiſhe purgatory in as few wordes as I can, that he may ſmell what a ſweete flowre it is. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be, it ſeemeth to ſauor very ſweetely with <hi>M. Fowler,</hi> &amp; therefore he doth very dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently place it, as one in euery petition of his Pſalter. Such is his charitie to their ſoules which are in purgatory, forſooth. But let vs ſee ſomewhat of this purgatorie, and partely euen as ſome of the maiſters of Rome haue wrytten thereof, I might deuide this matter into two braunches: firſt of prayer for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules of men departed out of this mortall life: then of this kinde of praier for the ſoules which are in purgatorie. But I will ſpeake of this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie prayer onely, for becauſe <hi>M. Fowler</hi> prayeth in his Pſalter for ſoules in purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry only, as though that they onely of all other ſoules departed had nede of this prayer. It is alſo confeſſed by ſome maiſters of that popiſh ſecte, that the prayers, or to vſe their owne
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3119:27"/> tearmes, the <hi>Suffrages</hi> of the church be auail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able only for ſoules in purgatory. They haue a reaſon for this their aſſertion, but I paſſe it ouer, becauſe that <hi>M. Fowler</hi> him ſelfe doth ſeeme to encline to the iudgement of thoſe his maiſters. For in the petitions of his Pſalter he maketh mention only of ſuch ſoules as are in purgatory. But if there be no purgatory at all, then are there no ſoules in purgatory to be prayed for. A vaine petition then it is in this Pſalter, and a needeleſſe diligence, when
<hi>M. Fowler</hi> ſheweth him ſelfe ſo diligent in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the ſoules in purgatory. Yea and it is more then vaine to abuſe the glorious name of Ieſu, and of his bitter paſſion to this his vanity of purgatory. Nowe lette vs conſider whether there be ſuch a purgatorie in which ſoules doe ſuffer (as they ſaye) the paines of ſcorching, broyling, or burninge, till they be purged from their ſinnes, and relieued by the charitable deedes of the liuinge, yea, or no. Let vs ſee who they were, that did firſt ſpeake of purgatory, and how it paſſed from them to ſome of the olde chriſtian wryters, which doe make mention thereof, but very doubtfully, and diuerſlie in their wrytinges. So ſhall it appeare vppon what fainte groundes pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie is founded. Firſt it is graunted that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3119:28"/> purgatory can not be proued by any place of the holy Scripture:<note place="margin">Petr. a ſoto Auguſt. Hy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ognoſt.</note> It is I ſay graunted by one Archepapiſt of this our age, and alſo by an olde writer of good antiquitie. But the holy Scripture is the rule whereby our prayers are to be framed, and it is the worde of trueth which doth truely teach vs of the true being of thinges. So that vnles God in his word did teach vs that there were a purgatory, we are not to beleue that there is any. And againe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that which God doth promiſe vs in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture we muſt grownd our faith in the prayers which we do make to God. For if we wil dewly regarde Gods good will with truſt that he will heare our prayers and graunt our requeſts, we muſt haue both a promiſe of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and a rule warrantinge the rightnes of our requeſtes in the moſt holy worde of God, without which we can not truely haue any faith or aſſurance of the hearing of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: without this knowledge we can make no true prayer. It is no true prayer therefore which thoſe men ſeeme to make which haue no vnderſtanding of Gods wil, nor truſt in his promiſes. Turkes, Iewes, and Papiſtes doe prate in their ignorance and vnbeleefe, but that prating is not right praying. Now then let vs admitte it as a trueth, which is as you
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3119:28"/> haue hearde confeſſed, that there is no holie Scripture, no word of God to warrant vs this purgatory, then haue we by the worde of God no aſſurance to aſſertaine vs that there be any ſoules in purgatory, nor commaundement of God giuen to vs to praye for ſoules in purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, nor promiſe to beleue that our prayers made for them can do them good. If we haue no aſſurance nor certeinety hereof, we can not pray for ſoules in purgatory. Wil you know then from whence this opinion of purgatorie doth come? The firſt and moſt auncient pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter thereof was (ſo farre as I learne) not God, but <hi>Plato</hi> the Philoſopher, a man which did not truely know God. His opinion of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie as <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth reporte it,<note place="margin">Libr. <hi>1.</hi> de praepar. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uang.</note> is the moſt auncient recorde that I haue red. <hi>Virgill</hi> the Pagan Poette hath ſpoken alſo of ſuch a thinge as purgatory is fained to be, but from <hi>Plato</hi> it ſhould ſeeme to be conueyed to other, who accordinge to their fantaſie layed the firſt platforme of a purgatory, euen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whereon the Papiſtes haue builded this their purgatorie. Which building by the papiſtes, is not yet ſo handſomely cowched together, but that their owne fathers aſſembled in the laſt councell of
<hi>Trent</hi> thought good by waye of correction to giue this admonition to them of their ſeete,<note place="margin">Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</note>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:3119:29"/> that they do not hereafter in their ſermons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the common people, handle the hard and dark queſtions touching purgatory, and that they ſhoulde not meddle with ſuch vncerteyne thinges touching purgatory as are thought to be falſe. They do alſo forbid them to handle thoſe thinges touching purgatory which doe ſauor of curioſitie, or concerne ſuperſticion, or ſauor of filthy lucre. And thoſe fathers as po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe as they were, doe yet commaunde them whome they may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund, that they let theſe thinges alone as offences. By this forbidding nowe, it appeareth that before this time, the purgatory Proctors vſed to publiſhe ſuche thinges of purgatory, and for it, as this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell now forbiddeth, elſe why doth it now for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them? And ſo by the wordes of Papiſtes them ſelues we may perceaue that they haue had among them ſuch Proctors for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, as haue handeled it ſo corruptly that they them ſelues are aſhamed thereof, and do forbid the like, and yet do theſe popiſh fathers in that councell vnderproppe this purgatory by their authoritie ſtill. But if they did meane in good earneſt, to take from their purgatory all ſuch thinges as are vncerteine and falſe, or curious or ſuperſtitious, and ſuch as ſerued for filthy gaine or lucre, let them I ſay pare al
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3119:29"/> theſe thinges from their purgatorie in good earneſt, and ſurely they ſhall leaue to their Pope then, ſuch a ſimple purgatory, as is not able to be a ſufficient pinfold to impounde a poore pigge. But as is ſayd, they and their fathers will needes maintaine their purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, for they haue taken in hande the defence thereof, and it ſerueth ſo well for their purſe, and purpoſe, that it deſerueth their defence. They ſaye that their Churche hathe learned it of the holie Scriptures. But I ſaye naye, and ſome of their owne men and their elders alſo doe ſaye naye, as is touched before. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe they them ſelues ſhewe vnto vs any one place of the holie Scriptures in whiche we are taught the ſame purgatorie, on which they doe conclude. This nowe is the manner of the catholike church (as papiſtes call their romiſhe Church) in their councelles to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude canons and articles of the faith without any Scripture. They tell vs that they haue it alſo of the auncient tradition of the fathers: hereof the reader ſhalbe informed more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Againe they ſay that this purgatorie is deliuered to them in holie councelles. A man would thinke that theſe Tridentine Prelates did meane ſome of the firſt auncient holy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, as that firſt councell holden at <hi>Nice,</hi> or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3119:30"/> that at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> or ſome of the other olde holy councells. But there is no mention made in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them either of this purgatorie, or of the ſoules in it, or howe they are to be releued by the doinges of liuinge men. Yea if ſearche be made in the Tomes of the councelles, it will be founde true (I thinke) that the firſt general councell which did ſet this purgatory on foote by concluding thereon, was that late councell begonne by Pope
<hi>Eugenius</hi> at <hi>Ferrara,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and ended at <hi>Florence</hi> about the yeare of our Lord <hi>1439.</hi> So young a thing among auncient councells is this proper ſpringalde their popiſh purgatory: before then it was not concluded in any auncient holie councell: ſo that yet the head of it neede not to be gray for age. It is no maruell then that the papiſtes haue now againe in <hi>Trent</hi> concluded thereon. For it ſerueth ſo well for their kitchins that they had rather looſe heauen it ſelfe, then this proper purgatory. And now our papiſts may ſay that it is a thinge decreed in councells, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence a ſeconde councell, nowe againe hathe concluded it: but yet ſuch councells as are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther auncient, nor holie. Thus pleaſeth it the papiſts now to burniſh and refreſh the old for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries of olde infidelles, and to ſette the ſame foorth as an article of their catholike faith.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3119:30"/> The opinions of Pagans touchinge purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſome auncient wryters ſithence the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Ieſus Chriſt and the time of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles haue repeated, as
<hi>Euſebius</hi> doth: ſome haue giuen their addition to them, as <hi>Origen</hi> and ſome other, and yet that purgatory was not like vnto this of papiſtes. For papiſts do allowe that the ſoules fried in the fier of their purgatory, may be releued by the deedes and helpes of liuing men. But this is not ſeene in the olde purgatory of <hi>Origen,</hi> nor in that of the Pagans ſo plainely as papiſtes now talke of it. When purgatory had once thus put in a foote into the church, it went forwarde yet for a good ſpace of time, but weakely and waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringely. The opinion thereof was cited by ſome followinge wryters after <hi>Origen.</hi> For
<hi>Ambroſe</hi> whoſe maner is (as ſome haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) to take many thinges out of
<hi>Origen,</hi> doth make mention of this purgatorie. So doth <hi>Hierome</hi> and alſo
<hi>Auguſtine,</hi> but very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly. For ſometime they doe as it were, but diſpute and reaſon of the matter, as if it were a queſtion to be doubted of: Sometime it is affirmed: Sometime that whiche one affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth: an other denyeth. And here is a peece of the falſe dealing of the papiſts to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. For their manner is to cyte the olde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3119:31"/> and their ſentences, in which they make this mention of purgatory as though they had with one conſent wrytten ſo of purgatory as them ſelues doe at this daye holde. They will not make knowne to the people in trueth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from whence this Purgatorie did firſt come, nor how it crept into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, nor how ſome of the olde fathers doubled about it. Some doubted of it, ſome denied it, all this I ſaye the Papiſtes nowe doe conceale, for the knowledge therof would marre their market, and not ſerue well for their kitchin. Therfore they doe ſtill drawe cloſely the ſayings of the olde writers to prope vppe this purgatory, as though there were no doubt in the matter, but that all the olde fathers did faithfully beleeue that to be true, which nowe they doe holde of purgatory. And yet becauſe their own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences doe beare them witnes, that they want ſufficient warrant of the worde of God &amp; true antiquity to vphold their purgatory, they haue bene driuen to make other ſhiftes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. And therefore where truth and antiquitie doe not ſerue their purpoſe, they haue buſied them ſelues to ſuſteine purgatory by other follyes, as by their forgeries of ſatisfactions, and by that ſame their preattie profitable deuiſe of praying for the dead. To this they haue added
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3119:31"/> ſtraunge viſions, voyces, and ſightes of ſuch as were by their conceites reuealed in purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and deliuered out of it (ſay they:) yea they haue added ſome ſuch ſtraunge ſightes as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing men haue ſeene in traunſes: and they do not ſtick alſo to father ſome of their owne new falſe forgeries for purgatory, vpon ſome wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of antiquitie which neuer taught any ſuch thinge. And thus for their purgatory, for proofe whereof they haue no direct worde of God, they drawe in fathers, yea and Angels, and ſpirites (they ſaye) but lyinge ſpirites (I ſaye.) They bringe in alſo deade men, yea and the ſculls of deade men to ſpeake to men liuinge on earthe for purgatory. And not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with all this they doe ſtill proceede, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better to ſetle this purgatory in their church as an article of their faithe, they make them ſelues ſo bold euen with God him ſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do draw his moſt holy word with new racking and wraſting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame out of time, to ſerue this their purpoſe: wherein verely they ſhew them ſelues to be corrupt handlers of the worde of God. Vpon theſe proppes did their purgatory ſtande ſtowtly till the light &amp; heate of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Goſpell of God did bewray it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it to aſhes. Then did this
<hi>Dagon</hi> fall before the Arke of the God of Iſraell, bleſſed
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3119:32"/> be his name for it. And nowe that they ſee their purgatory doth beginne to decaye, they doe roare and crye for greefe, and doe ſtyll ſeeke to maintayne it by newe additions, or reparations, ſo loth they are to haue it ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, that it ſhoulde ſerue their turne no more. Some tyme they tell vs of the kinde of thoſe ſinnes which are to be purged in purgatory: ſome time they tell vs of the greatnes of the paines which ſoules ſuffer there: ſome time of the releefe which ſoules doe feele there: ſome time they tell vs of the place where purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is. But theſe their tales be not all one, nor they them ſelues in telling theſe tales doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in one. For towching the place where this purgatory is: Some of them haue found this purgatory (as they ſaye) in Irelande, and this they call the <hi>Purgatory of Patricke,</hi> vnto which alſo they ſay that once they had a keye. I knowe not whether they haue loſte it. And in this purgatory one luſtie Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion <hi>Noble Nicolas</hi> (as they ſaye) trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and did ſee the ſtraunge paynes and ſights which were in it. One other purgatory their holy Sainct <hi>Odilo</hi> did finde for them in the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of <hi>Sicily</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fiery hil <hi>Aetna.</hi> And of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention by the good aduiſe of their pope
<hi>Iohn</hi> did ſpring vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſolemne feaſt <hi>of al ſoules,</hi> &amp; al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:3119:32"/> buſy paines y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do take about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, which yet the church of Chriſt both could &amp; did well ſpare aboue the ſpace of one thowſand yeares after Chriſtes aſcenſion, although the popiſhe ſinagogue can not now ſpare it for pinchinge their bellies not one yere. Theſe men not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with theſe purgatories, and fearinge the ruine of it without it be continually repayred, haue gotten of late the fauorable help toward this worke, of a new Archbiſhop of theirs na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Aolaus Magnus:</hi> This man hath founde a third purgatory in the Iland of <hi>Thyle</hi> which we call Iſelande, for there (ſayth he) are hills which haue ſnow on their toppes and burning fyer at their foote, and he telleth vs that there is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place to purge ſoules. Thus groweth the popiſhe purgatory in errour and ignoraunce, and getteth grounde ſtill more &amp; more among ignoraunt men. This popiſh palace of purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory ſhould be very large truely, if it did reach ſo farre as is <hi>Iſeland</hi> from
<hi>Sicily.</hi> What fyer there is I knowe not, but ſurely there is good ſtoare of ſea water betwene theſe forenamed Ilandes <hi>Irelande, Sicily,</hi> and <hi>Iſelande,</hi> yet all the water which is in the ſea will not quenche that purgatorie which the Pope and his kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin clarkes haue blowen and ſette on fyer to roaſt their meate. Thus much of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3119:33"/> and growing of this purgatory haue I ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrytten, that the reader may knowe out of what forge this purgatory is flowen of which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> maketh ſo often mention in his Pſalter, &amp; doth ſo bitterly pray for the ſoules which are in it. But as I ſayd before, if there be no purgatory at all, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are there no ſoules in it nor any thinge elſe: and will <hi>M. Fowler</hi> teache his ſchollers to praye to God for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge? This purgatory hath no grounde of the worde of God: We haue neither co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to pray, nor promiſe to be heard, if we do pray for ſoules in purgatory, therefore we can neither doe the one, nor beleue the other. He then that will praye with <hi>M. Fowler</hi> for ſoules in purgatory, prayeth without faith, which is a faithleſſe labor, at the leaſt, though I ſay no more. But he that wil conſider right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what a faulte it is, for a man to preſent him ſelfe before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maieſty of God, to make praier to him for nothing, for a forgery &amp; falſe thing, it wil make him (I trow) afeard to make ſuch ſtraunge prayers, though <hi>M. Fowler</hi> be very buſie with them. But nowe will I leaue this purgatory, I will in this treatiſe touche it no more, ſuppoſing that this which I haue ſayd, is ſufficient to vnfolde the forgerie of this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe poppet. <hi>M. Fowler</hi> teacheth him which
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3119:33"/> will daunce after his pype to pray: <hi>That he may execute the workes of vertue, whereby he may come to euerlaſting ioy and felicitie.</hi> To ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe vertue to the pleaſing of God, is a good thinge, and our dewtie. But if <hi>Maiſter Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> doth meane to teach his Reader to do this, with this minde, to hope thereby to come to, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to gaine, and to obtayne euerlaſting ioye and felicitie, this is, but to labour vainely and prowdly, to get that by our doing, which is freely giuen to the elect by the mercie of God in Ieſus Chriſt. For life euerlaſting is the gifte of God by Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi>
6.</note> as thApoſtle teacheth. Ieſus Chriſt is the onely waye, that true way by which that happy theefe of whome we reade <hi>Luke 23.</hi> went into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. Ieſus is he only and alone, by &amp; thorough whome euerlaſting life is giuen to the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. The chriſtian reader may wel perceaue therefore wherein this petition fayleth. Then followeth a petition in which he teacheth his reader to pray thus: <hi>Graunt me firme purpoſe mercifull Ieſu to amend my life &amp; to recompenſe for thoſe yeares which I haue mispent to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spleaſure of thee in euill thoughtes, delectations, &amp;c. Alſo in breaking thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I haue deſerued damnation &amp; thine enimitie.</hi> To pray for amendement of life is neceſſary.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3119:34"/> But in that which followeth, <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth fowly abuſe the holy name of Ieſus. For to pray to Ieſus to haue a firme purpoſe to make recompenſe for thoſe ſinnes whereby we haue deſerued damnation, is to pray for purpoſe to deny and forſake the ſaluation which we haue in Ieſus. For Ieſus is he which doth ſaue his people from their ſinnes. And therefore he is called Ieſus. <hi>M. Fowler</hi> hath giuen vs (as he ſayth)
<hi>A Pſalter of Ieſus,</hi> &amp; he ſemeth to make great accompt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> often repeating of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name <hi>Ieſus.</hi> But now he doth ſhew him ſelfe not only not to know what Ieſus doth meane, but to be willing to draw his reader to deny that Ieſus is Ieſus in deede, which is to deny the Lorde that bought him. We haue learned that in that redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which Ieſus hath wrought for his elect, he onely hath made the full recompenſe to God by him ſelfe alone for all their ſinnes, and therefore he is their Ieſus, and ſo is moſt truely called Ieſus. Ieſus did giue him ſelfe for vs, when we could giue nothing in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe for our ſelues, he did giue his body to be broken &amp; his bloode to be ſhed for the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our ſinnes, for which we could make no recompenſe. He did beare the paines due to vs for our ſinnes, and as the Prophet ſayth <hi>Iſai 53.</hi> he hath borne our infirmities &amp; carried our
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3119:34"/> ſorrowes, he was wounded for our tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, he was broken for our iniquities: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement of our peace was vppon him, &amp; with his ſtripes are we healed. Here is the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe made for ſinne ſet forth, and this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe verely did Ieſus make in his owne bleſſed body. In if he payd the price of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and made that only ſatis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cing, and fully ſufficing recompenſe for vs, wherein his owne ſelf did beare our ſinnes to his body on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree <hi>1. Pet. 2.</hi> &amp; by this reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penſe by him made we are ſet free, for by his wounds are we hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Sithence <hi>Fowler</hi> is not content with this recompenſe thus made by Ieſus for vs, but aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an other, let him tell me wherein that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe which Ieſus Chriſt hath made for vs is imperfect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if it be imperfect, ſhew wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? If it be not imperfect but moſt full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, then what meaneth <hi>M. Fowler</hi> to pray for full purpoſe to make any other recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe him ſelf for his ſinnes. Again I would know what it is, that he or any childe of <hi>Adam</hi> can giue to God to make a recompenſe for his and their ſinns? What Ieſus hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we know. Now let vs know what <hi>Fowler</hi> hath to giue? <hi>Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> can giue nothing verely but that which is corrupt, but ſuch thinges are not auaileable, they are no recompenſe at all for ſinnes. And
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3119:35"/> therefore God of his great mercy prouidinge better for vs, then we coulde do for our ſelues, hath giuen vnto vs Chriſt Ieſus, to make, and to be the recompenſe for vs. For we are not as <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſayeth redeemed with corruptible thinges as ſiluer and golde, but with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloode of Chriſt. For Ieſus hath with this moſt precious price made full recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for vs, &amp; thereby hath he ſo fully redeemed vs, that therfore he is become the author &amp; prince of our ſaluation, our redeemer, our Sauiour, to him only do we giue the glory and praiſe of &amp; for this worke of our ſaluation wrought by him ſelfe for vs. God our heauenly father hath ſet forth his ſonne Ieſus to be a reconciliation through faith in his blood <hi>Rom. 3.</hi> It is Ieſus only which did giue his life a ranſome for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ath.</hi>
20.</note> Our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is his life, which Ieſus did giue for the price, raunſome, and recompence of our deliuerie. For Chriſt onely is he, in whom as the Apoſtle ſaith we haue rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption through his blood, euen the forgiuenes of our ſinnes, <hi>Colo. 1.</hi> And Ieſus alone is the recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation and attonement for our ſinnes <hi>1. Ioh. 2.</hi> Thus as we are taughte, we doe learne of God him ſelfe, that it is Ieſus alone, which doth deliuer vs from that dampnation which through our ſinnes we doe deſerue, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3119:35"/> recompence, which he hath already made for vs in his owne moſt bitter death, and bloody paſſion. It is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood of Chriſt which through the eternall ſpirite offered him ſelfe without ſpotte to God, which purgeth our conſcience from dead workes, to ſerue the liuinge God. It is Ieſus Chriſt who hath appeared once to take away ſinne, by the ſacrifice of him ſelfe. <hi>Heb. 9.</hi> Now as the ſame Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>Heb. 10.</hi> Where the remiſſion of theſe thinges is, there is no more offeringe for ſinne: and I ſay where the recompence for ſinne is thus made by Ieſus, there is no more recompence to be made for ſinne. How dare <hi>Fowler</hi> then teache vs to require to haue a firme purpoſe in vs to make our ſelues a recompence for this which Ieſus only both coulde doe, and alſo did fully, &amp; ſufficiently for vs? What is this elſe, but to aſke of Ieſus a firme purpoſe to renounce and forſake him? It is nothing elſe verely, but to forſake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> redemption which we haue in Chriſt Ieſus, &amp; to repoſe our ſelues vppon our owne making of recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to pray as <hi>Fowler</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth. But what Prophet, what Apoſtle, or Sainct did euer ſo pray? or taught vs to pray? That which none hath done euer, <hi>Fowler</hi> now dare do. <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth humbly to the Lorde in his Pſalter that he will forget and forgiue
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3119:36"/> the faults of his youth <hi>Pſal. 25.</hi> And he reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth that the Lord hath forgiuen him his ſins, that he hath forgotten the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath remoued them from him as farre as is the Eaſt from the Weſt: that he hath throwne them into the bottome of the ſea
<hi>Pſal. 103. Dauid</hi> prayeth not to haue a firme purpoſe to make recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for his ſins, but reſteth in the bleſſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of his ſinnes giuen him by God of his free goodnes &amp; mercy through Chriſt Ieſus. And againe, <hi>Dauid</hi> in the <hi>Pſal.
31.</hi> confeſſeth of him ſelfe this: I acknowledge my ſinne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, neither hide I mine iniquitie, for I thought I will confeſſe againſt my ſelfe my wickednes vnto the Lorde, and thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iniquity of my ſinne. Thus doth <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in his Pſalter, ſinge an other manner of Pſalme then <hi>Fowler</hi> doth in this his Pſalter. For the true Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of his ſinnes, and reioyceth in this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God did forgiue him, which is ſuch a thinge to be deſired, that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth immediatly in that Pſalme: Therefore ſhall euery one that is godly make his prayer vnto thee &amp;c. What accompt then ſhall we make of <hi>Fowler</hi> who prayeth not for this, but cleane contrarie to this? for he will haue a firme purpoſe to make him ſelfe a recompence for his owne ſinnes.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3119:36"/> Surely neither is this prayer of <hi>Fowlers</hi> like to that of the godly, nor him ſelf godly in this praying. For if euery one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is godly prayeth for forgiuenes of ſins, <hi>Fowler</hi> is vngodly who prayeth not for forgiueneſſe, but for a firme purpoſe to make a recompenſe for his ſinnes. The holy children of God are all moſt holily taught by Ieſus our very Ieſus and Sauior to pray, <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes.</hi> This is an other manner of thing then to pray for a firme purpoſe to make our ſelues reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penſe for our ſinnes. Simple is he that will forſake that forme of prayer which Ieſus Chriſte hath taught, and holy <hi>Dauid</hi> vſed in his Pſalter, <hi>Dauid</hi> (I ſay) who was that ſweete Pſalme ſinger of Iſraell <hi>2. Sam. 23.</hi> &amp; will follow this faithles fiddle of <hi>Fowler.</hi> Simple is he that will forſake that recompenſe which Ieſus Chriſt hath once made for him &amp; truſt to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe of his own making. This were fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to fal from Chriſt &amp; to runne headlong into the dungeon of deſpaire. Al the Angels &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſpirites in heauen, all the men in earth can not make ſuch a recompenſe. Onely Ieſus Chriſt, Ieſus (I ſay) alone was able to make, and did make the full recompenſe for ſinne, &amp; did it fully for the faithfull, &amp; therfore he hath founde euerlaſting ſaluation for them which
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3119:37"/> ſhalbe ſaued, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle ſayth <hi>Heb. 9.</hi> which truely he could not haue gayned vnles the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe which he made for them had bene fully ſufficient. Now to take this work of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king recompenſe into our owne handes, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deny, or to dout of the fulnes of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe which Ieſus Chriſt hath made for vs, and this to doe, is to robbe Ieſus of his glory, and the robber doth robbe him ſelfe of comfort and ſaluation in Chriſt, &amp; ſo doth but deceaue him ſelf, and double his owne ſinne &amp; damnation. Yet thus woulde <hi>M. Fowler</hi> haue his Reader to pray to Ieſu, to haue not onely his purpoſe, but his firme purpoſe to make him ſelf recompenſe for his ſinnes, which is to robbe Ieſus of his glory, &amp; to be him ſelf a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit to him ſelf, &amp; to make his way to moſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; certein damnation. If <hi>M. Fowler</hi> miſtruſt the recompenſe which Ieſus hath made, and doth deſire to make his owne recompenſe for his owne ſinnes: then doth he not beleue that Ieſus hath made either any recompenſe at al, or not a full recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe for his ſinnes, which is a point of plaine infidelitie. Such as floweth in the Romiſh Catholike Church. This peece of poyſon lyeth in this Pſalter of <hi>M. Fowlers,</hi> euen this robbing of Ieſus in <hi>M. Fowler</hi> his <hi>Pſalter of Ieſus.</hi> An other petition followteh
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3119:37"/> containing theſe wordes. <hi>Graunt me the ſeuen giftes of the holy Ghost, the eyght beatitudes, the foure Cardinall vertues, and in receiuing of the Sacrament deuoutly to dispoſe me. <hi>M. Fowler</hi>
               </hi> delighteth him ſelfe greately in ſett numbers, and yet he is no good Arithmetrician. When he ſpeaketh of the ſeuen gifts of the holy ghoſt he ſhould haue tolde his Reader what they be, and where he learned that there be but ſeuen. Surely we knowe that there are many more giftes then ſeauen which the holy Ghoſt doth giue to the elect children of God, I ſay many more. Likewiſe I ſaye of the <hi>Beatitudes</hi> of which he ſpeaketh as though there were no more but eight. It may be that I am ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that I doe not know to what places of the holy ſcriptures <hi>M. Fowler</hi> had his eye in theſe his ſet numbers. Therefore let him name the places him ſelfe, &amp; proue to vs if he can, either that they do containe theſe preciſe numbers of ſeauen or eight, and no more, or that there be no more giftes of the holy Ghoſt but ſeauen, nor more beatitudes but eight. In the meane tyme the Chriſtian Reader, which loueth with godly reuerence to ſearche the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in ſearchinge ſhall finde that there be many more giftes of the holy Ghoſt then ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp; many more beatitudes then eight. Let
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3119:38"/> not him therfore be thus abridged of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes by <hi>Maiſter Fowler,</hi> if he doe loue ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification and bleſſednes. <hi>M. Fowler</hi> ſeemeth alſo to haue ſome ſmattering of Philoſophy in telling vs of foure <hi>cardinal vertues.</hi> But ſome of his Maiſters in teaching vertues haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the three diuine or Theologicall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, &amp; this he might haue learned in his pops Primer lately printed, and haue named them <hi>faith, hope and charitie.</hi> Wherein they doe ſpeake more like Diuines then
<hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth either like a Diuine or good Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher. Amonge the Philoſophers them ſelues he might haue found more vertues then foure. He might alſo haue done ſomewhat for the helpe of his ſimple Reader for whoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure he hath made this Pſalter, if he had told him what thoſe vertues were, and why they be called <hi>Cardinall vertues.</hi> For a ſimple man may thinke that they are ſo called of the Romiſh Cardinals, a ſect of men moſt voyd of vertues, as by their particular doings may be eaſily founde out. And to ſpeake of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues needefull to a Chriſtian, there are many more then foure which a chriſtian is to learne in the bleſſed booke of God, the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture I meane. So <hi>M. Fowler</hi> in this peece of his Pſalter ſtriketh but like a bungeling
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3119:38"/> fidler, not cleane, not full, but ſtriketh very ſhorte, and doth but fumble &amp; dally with them, whom he would haue dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce after his pipe. In his fourth petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he teacheth them which are minded to play on his Pſalter, to ſay, <hi>Graunt me the ſpirite of penaunce, contrition, confeſſion &amp; ſatisfaction, to obtaine thy grace, &amp; from fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſinne to purge me.</hi> Trewe penaunce we doe know, and pray that it may be truly practiſed: we do alſo know thoſe tearmes which <hi>M. Fow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler</hi> doth vſe: They are the ſame, by which the popiſhe ſchoolemen doe ſet foorth their three partes of their Sacrament of penaunce. But this their deuiſe is already ſo euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vndone, and the filthe and forgery thereof, ſo vnfolded by the learned wryters of our age, that I will no further meddle therewith, then to referre the reader to the readinge of the <hi>fourth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the thirde booke of the Inſtitutions of M. Caluin,</hi> which if he will diligently read o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, he ſhall perceaue that in this popiſh par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition is no perfect penance, &amp; that this peece of worke as <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth penne it, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meete to haue place in the prayer of a trewe Chriſtian, howe meete ſoeuer it be, to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in this Pſalter of <hi>M. Fowler.</hi> And where he addeth that by this parted Penaunce, he might obtaine Gods grace, he knoweth not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3119:39"/> verily what grace meaneth. For as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle teacheth: If grace be of workes, it is no more grace: he falleth from grace that doth by his workes thruſt on him ſelfe, to gaine, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue merite and gette grace. In the fifte pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition he teacheth vs to pray thus:
<hi>The catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like obſeruances of the church make me to kepe truely.</hi> What he meaneth by theſe catholike obſeruaunces, I dare not take on me to iudge, I knowe them not. But if he doe by them meane thoſe fiue commaundementes of the church, which his frend &amp; companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>M. Vaws</hi> hath ſet foorth in his Catechiſme, in which he doth but bungel, and woulde faine imitate the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> in their Catechiſme. Yf theſe be the catholike obſeruances of the church of which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> ſpeaketh, or if he doe meane thoſe preceptes of the church which his Pope <hi>Pius</hi> hathe packed together in his newe Primer, I aunſwere thus. Firſt, we do deny that they be catholike: Then that they be any obſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the true church of Chriſt. As for that romiſh church which both hath and doth take vppon her to deliuer ſuch commaundementes as God did neuer giue to his church, we doe abhorre that proude harlot, and all her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, neither hath a Chriſtian any warraunt of Gods worde to aſſure his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3119:39"/> either to make this petition, whiche is here ſette downe by <hi>M. Fowler,</hi> nor promiſe to be hearde, if he make it, and therefore it is to be lefte to the deuiſers of it. And ſurely this his petition, doth not agree with the firſt pece of the next petition followinge, that is: <hi>Make my ſoule obedient to holy doctrine.</hi> He whoſe ſoule is made obedient to holy doctrine, doth deteſt all ſuche vnholie doctrines, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunces as men doe deliuer out of their owne deuiſes, ſuche as are the commaundementes and obſeruaunces of the catholike churche of <hi>Rome,</hi> and he prayeth God to keepe him from them, he can not praye to keepe or obey them. In the ſeauenth petition, he hathe put in this for a prayer: <hi>Thy bleſſed mother be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatrice for me, and purchaſe me a contrite hearte, for that I haue offended thee.</hi> You haue heard before howe <hi>Maiſter Fowler</hi> hath called the Lord Ieſus, the Mediator of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as though this were all that is in the Lord Ieſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And you haue heard how I haue proued that our Lorde Ieſus is the Mediator of our ſaluation, and is alſo our Mediator of interceſſion. Now <hi>Maiſter Fowler</hi> as though Ieſus the onely Mediatour did not content him, findeth vs out a newe Mediatour the Virgine
<hi>Marie,</hi> whome he will haue to be a
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3119:40"/> mediatrice for him, and a purchaſer for him. But we chriſtians do knowe, no other Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor nor purchaſer for vs, but one, euen that one only Lord Ieſus the ſonne of the virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> for he is the Mediator betwene God and man, euen that man Chriſt Ieſus. Ieſus is as the Apoſtle calleth him, <hi>He. 12.</hi> the Mediator of the New Teſtament. The Goſpell &amp; word of the New Teſtament doth teach vs to know Ieſus to be the Mediator of al them, which do appertaine to the New Teſtament, &amp; are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued into that couenaunt of life. It doth not aſſigne vs any other Mediator, not the virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> not any Sainct, nor Angell. We dare not take this office from the ſonne, and giue it to the mother: we will not forſake the ſonne who is our certaine, ſure, and only Mediator, and go to the mother, who hath no ſuch office committed vnto her. We learne alſo that a contrite harte is wroughte in the electe by the ſpirite and word of God. We doe not knowe howe the virgine
<hi>Mary</hi> can purchaſe this for vs. Againe, in that petition he placeth theſe wordes:
<hi>All thy Sainctes pray for me, that I be not ſeparate from thee, and their bleſſed fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhippe in the heauenly city.</hi> Thoughe it be graunted to <hi>M. Fowler</hi> that the Sainctes in heauen doe pray for vs, yet hathe he giuen vs
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3119:40"/> no warrant of the worde of God, to aſſure our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, either to make our prayers to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or to pray the Lord Ieſus to ſpeake to them, or to appoint them to pray for vs. The Lorde Ieſus prayed for <hi>Peter,</hi> that his faith might not faile, if it had failed he had bien ſeparated from the Lorde Chriſt. Lette them therefore whiche feare this ſeparation, pray the Lorde Ieſus to be euen ſo good to them in this point as he was to
<hi>Peter.</hi> For Chriſt prayed not for the Apoſtles only, but for all them which ſhal beleue in him truly. I pray not for theſe alone (ſayth he) but for all them alſo which ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in me through their worde, <hi>Ioh. 17.</hi> We know that the Lorde Ieſus him ſelfe maketh interceſſion for vs, and with that we doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelues, &amp; therefore we leaue Saincts to <hi>M. Fowler.</hi> In the eight petition he putteth in this peece: <hi>VVhen I offende thee, ſmite me not with ſodaine death I beſeeche thee:</hi> and in the fifteenth petition, he prayeth likewiſe: <hi>from ſodaine death and vnforeſeene Lorde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue me.</hi> What meaneth <hi>M. Fowler</hi> to aſke this one thinge thus twiſe? Woulde he haue the worlde vnderſtande that he is afrayed of death, and afrayed to dye?<note place="margin">Cip. ſerm. de mort.</note> He feareth death ſayeth <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that is vnwillinge to goe to Chriſt. <hi>M. Fowler</hi> maketh by his Pſalter a
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3119:41"/> ſhew as though he were well acquainted with the name of Ieſus, and is he (I ſay) afrayd to die? Then he is not well acquainted with Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus himſelfe, how buſie ſo euer he be with his name. For that feare is of want of faith in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus verely. This feare hath bene ſeene in ſome cloiſterers, if all be true that they doe wryte, which doe wryte the liues of cloyſterers. For of cloyſterers we may ſee ſome which haue earneſtly deſired the puttinge of,<note place="margin">Vit. patr.</note> of death, and the prolonging of life. But yet other of them haue corrected this feare in them ſelues by faith, as they wryte of
<hi>Hylarion</hi> who feeling him ſelfe to be afrayed of death, ſayed to him ſelfe: <hi>O ſoule thou haſt ſerued Chriſt theſe foureſcore yeares, and art thou now afrayed to goe out. Exi quia miſericors eſt:</hi> that is: <hi>Go out for he is mercifull.</hi> This correction of feare by faith in Chriſt is much better then <hi>M. Fowlers</hi> feareful prayer. But this tearme, <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſeene death</hi> may giue vs occaſion to thinke that <hi>M. Fowler</hi> and ſuch as he is, do lead a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſecure, and careleſſe life, which doe neuer foreſee death. That manne that ſo leadeth his life, that he doth not in his life time foreſee his death draw on him dayly, is maruelouſly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Blinde he is which can not foreſee death which is daily ſeene, and dull he is, whome ſo
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3119:41"/> many warninges of death giuen can not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to death. The life of a chriſtian hath in it a continuall premeditation and foreſight of death, &amp; that death which is ſo foreſeene right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhall not (I trow) be ſuddaine when it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. Neither ſhall any death be ſuddaine to him, or vnforeſeene of him, that is both godly and dayly prepared to dye. Therefore let <hi>M. Fowler</hi> acquaint his hearte with that deſire which the Apoſtle had in his breaſt, when he deſired to be loaſed and to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt. And let him teache his reader that leſſon, after that he hath well digeſted it him ſelfe, which the holy Apoſtle teacheth <hi>2. Cor. 5.</hi> That is, that the faithfull doe ſigh, deſiringe to be clothed with their houſe which is from heauen. They haue their deſire that mortalitie might be ſwallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vppe of life, and to remoue out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and to dwell with the Lord. If <hi>M. Fowler</hi> will learne to acquainte him ſelfe well with the godly deſires of the faithfull, truely then he ſhall not neede to make this petition of his either ſingle or double, as nowe he doth. The firſt parte of the ninth petition is: <hi>Ieſu graunt me grace for to remember perfectly the daunger of death, and the great acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt which I muſt giue to thee, and to diſpoſe me that my ſoule may be acceptable to thee &amp; to thy glorious mother the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3119:42"/> bleſſed virgin Mary.</hi> The right remembraunce of death is very neceſſary and profitable to the liuing. But it is ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that <hi>M. Fowler</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Ieſus ſo to diſpoſe him that his ſoule may be acceptable to him and to his glorious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the virgine <hi>Mary.</hi> It is ſufficient truely that our ſoules be made acceptable to God our father by the Lorde Ieſus, for ſo be they ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly accepted to ſaluation, &amp; they which are made ſo acceptable, can not but be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to the companie of that bleſſed virgine <hi>Mary,</hi> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saincts which are in heauen with her, &amp; to all the Angells alſo: why Ieſus ſhold make our ſoules, which by his owne grace are accepted to ſaluation, acceptable to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I knowe not, vnleſſe <hi>M. Fowler</hi> thinketh that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing which Ieſus Chriſt doth accept, his mother may, or wil miſlike. But I thinke not ſo euell of that bleſſed virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth. For I thinke that ſhe doth rather adore the grace of her ſonne Ieſus, by which he doth accept our ſoules to ſaluation, then either miſlike it, or ioyne with him in the office, and authority of acceptinge. It followeth, in the ſame petition: <hi>Then with the aſſiſtance of thy glorious Angell Sainct Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaell, deliuer me from the daunger of my ghoſtly enemie.</hi> This name of the holy Angell
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3119:42"/> we know, &amp; we know alſo that the deliuerer of the faithfull from their ghoſtly enemy the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, is Ieſus Chriſt alone, for he thorough death did deſtroy him that hadde the power of death, that is the deuill as the Apoſtle ſayeth, <hi>Heb. 2.</hi> And
<hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſayth, <hi>1. Ioh. 3.</hi> That for this purpoſe the ſonne of God appeared that he might loaſe the workes of the deuill, he it is by whom only it is, that the God of power treadeth Sathan vnder the feete of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.</note> Why doth <hi>M. Fowler</hi> flee from this grace, and power of the Lord Ieſus to <hi>S. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaell.</hi> We knowe not who hathe aſſigned <hi>S. Michaell</hi> the Archangell to this office to be a deliuerer of ſoules in daunger of death, from the daunger of the Ghoſtlie enemie. If <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Fowler</hi> liſteth to make him ſelfe bolde to aſſigne offices to Aungelles in heauen, it is but a popiſhe pryde. It followeth: <hi>And thee my good Aungell I beſeeche than to helpe me.</hi> And what doe you ſaye <hi>Maiſter Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> to your badde Aungell? will you ſaye no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to him? you do dreame in popery that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery manne hath his two Angells, that is his good Angell, &amp; his bad Angell, as al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde knoweth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.</note> But in the worde of trueth we doe learne &amp; by it we know that God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Aungelles to be miniſtringe ſpirites
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:3119:43"/> ſent forthe to miniſter for their ſakes which ſhall be heires of ſaluation, but that each man hath his ſeuerall Angell appoynted to helpe him I doe not yet certeinly know. But I will leaue this queſtion to the time and place of more full knowledge. And in the meane tyme till I doe know it, I would faine learne of <hi>M. Fowler,</hi> where he hath learned to pray to his good Aungell, or to any Aungell. We knowe that the holy Angells doe not ſuffer men to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore or worſhip them <hi>Apoca. 21.</hi> Howe will they then admit that men ſhould pray to them? Will <hi>M. Fovvler</hi> pray to them whether they will or no? Prayer is a ſeruice which we are taught to doe to God, to whom Chriſt Ieſus commaundeth vs to pray. But neither Ieſus nor his Apoſtles, did euer teache vs in any place to pray to our good Angell. Who then hath taught <hi>Maiſter Fowler</hi> to praye to his good Angell for helpe thus ſolemnly? Let <hi>M. Fowler</hi> tell vs this in trueth, or els we will turne it ouer to him ſelfe, as one of his owne dreames and forgeries. In the tenth petition he ſayth: <hi>Ieſu ſende me here my purgatory and preſerue me from thoſe torments of fier which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall puniſh ſinne and iniquitie.</hi> I will not, without further proofe, preſume to ſay that <hi>M. Fowler</hi> is fallen into that beaſtly filth of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras,</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:3119:43"/> who dreamed of a monſtrous kinde of purgatory and purginge of ſoules in this mortall life. But let <hi>M. Fowler</hi> awake out of his owne dreame and tell vs, howe and where he hath found vs out this new purgatory, that is ſuch a one as he doth praye to haue in this life here. Of which belike he is not greatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, for be teacheth his ſcholler to praye for it tenne times together. But this is not that purgatory (I trow) out of which he prayeth in euery one of the petitions in his Pſalter ſo bitterly to haue ſoules deliuered, nor yet is it that purgatory of which his catholike fathers in the laſt councell of <hi>Trent</hi> doe conclude: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this fire which doth euer puniſh ſinne, that fire of the popiſh purgatory. For if it doe euer puniſh ſinne, then doth it neuer ceaſe nor ende. But the fire of the popiſh purgatory hath an ende, as Papiſtes them ſelues doe ſay, if they ſay truely. And therfore a Maiſter of that ſect doth call that their purgatory fire <hi>ignem tranſitorium,</hi> a fire tranſitory or paſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. This purgatory then, is none of thoſe purgatories of which we haue hearde before, neither is this fire that fire of purgatory. It is needefull therefore that <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doe tell vs what fierles purgatory this is which he ſo bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiely prayeth to haue in this life. We muſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3119:44"/> know what it is, before we doe pray for it. If it ſhall pleaſe him to tell vs, what that purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory is which he calleth <hi>my purgatory, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to haue it in this life,</hi> we ſhall conſider the matter more diligently with him, in the mean time I leaue it to him ſelfe. It followeth in his Pſalter: <hi>Mother of God, Patriarches, &amp;c.</hi> (he reckneth vp a number of Sainctes) <hi>I offer me to your merits and beſeech you to pray for me, &amp; at my paſſing helpe to protect me.</hi> I ſuppoſe <hi>M. Fowler</hi> will accompt
<hi>Abraham</hi> to be one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Patriarches to whom he prayeth. But what if <hi>Abraham</hi> doe not know him? In the prophecie of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaica. 63.</hi> We reade of ſome who in their prayer to God ſeeme to be ſturred vppe the more vehemently to praye vnto God himſelfe for helpe, by this doubtles (ſay they) thou art our father, though <hi>Abraham</hi> be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of vs, and <hi>Iſraell</hi> knoweth vs not, yet thou O Lord, art our father and redemer, thy name is for euer. Loe here is a people which doe offer them ſelues to God their father, and ſay that the Patriarches
<hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> doe not know them. If theſe Patriarches doe not knowe nor vnderſtande of the liuing men, what other Patriarches doe it? Let <hi>M. Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> tell vs this, and alſo let him tell vs by what warrant of the word of God, he doth teach his
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:3119:44"/> Reader to offer him ſelfe thus to the merites of the mother of God, of the Patriarches, Prophetes, Sainctes &amp;c. We are taughte to offer our ſelues to God. The ſacrifices and offeringes whiche are to be made of our ſelues, are to be made to God alone whoſe we are <hi>Rom. 12.</hi> And <hi>S. Peter 1. Peter 2.</hi> doth teache that the beleuing Chriſtians are made a ſpirituall houſe and holy prieſthoode to offer vppe ſacrifices acceptable to God by Ieſus Chriſt. We haue not learned to offer our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to the merits of the mother of God or of any Patriarche, Prophet or Sainct liuinge or departed. There were a kinde of olde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes which did make offeringes and ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> as
<hi>Epiphanius</hi> doth write.<note place="margin">Epiph. li. <hi>3.</hi> tom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> This offring of which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, ſauoreth ſtrongly of that old hereſie, and therefore I leaue it as a ſtincking ſacrifice to <hi>M. Fowler</hi> him ſelfe. We haue likewiſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the booke of God to truſt to be ſaued by the merits of Chriſt alone, and belike <hi>M. Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> hath heard of ſuch a thing. For he doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly in the ſame petition ſay. <hi>My Lorde Ieſus crucified for me, by the merites of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious paſſion, I beſeech thee graunt me theſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions.</hi> And him ſelfe doth ſaye in an other place of his Pſalter: <hi>Thy mercy and thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3119:45"/> my Sauiour, euer be betwene them,</hi> (Gods wrathe and iudgement he meaneth)
<hi>and me.</hi> Why doth <hi>M. Fowler</hi> like an Infidell in the tenth petition ſhewe him ſelfe to miſtruſt the merites of Ieſus, and doth therein offer him ſelfe to the merits of Gods mother and other Sainctes, and nowe doth commit him ſelfe to the merits of Ieſus. Is not this a fowle iarre and diſcord in this Pſalter of his? I ſay again that we Chriſtians haue learned to truſt to the merits of Ieſus Chriſt alone, and to pray him to make interceſſion for vs. We haue not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to pray Sainctes to make interceſſion for vs, for this is to depart from Chriſt. We haue learned to pray the Lord Ieſus both in our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing &amp; in our paſſing to protect vs. We haue not learned in any teacher of truth to aske this protection of the mother of God, or other Sainctes. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> hauing him ſelfe good hope in Gods might &amp; mercy, doth both commende him ſelfe, and teacheth vs to commend our ſelues into the handes of God the Lorde our Redeemer <hi>Pſal. 31.</hi> Into thy handes (ſayth he) I doe commend my ſpirit, for thou haſt redeemed me O Lorde God of truth. Thus
<hi>Dauid</hi> doth acknowledge God to be his protector and ſafe keeper, he doth not praye the mother of God, he doth not praye
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3119:45"/> Sainctes to protect him. The ſame <hi>Dauid Pſal. 121.</hi> ſayth. The Lord is thy keeper, the Lord is thy ſhadow at thy right hand. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the Lord ſhall preſerue thee from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, he ſhall keepe thy ſoule. The Lorde ſhall preſerue thy going out and comming in from hence forth and for euer. He ſayeth likewiſe <hi>Pſal. 97.</hi> The Lorde preſerueth the ſoules of his Sainctes, he will deliuer them from the hand of the wicked. The ſame Prophet <hi>Dauid Pſal. 18.</hi> doth with thankefull hart to God and full mouth confeſſe this. Thou haſt giuen me (ſayth he) the ſhielde of thy ſaluation, and thy right hande hath ſtaide me. But what did <hi>M. Fowler</hi> neuer reade, neither theſe, nor thoſe ſweete ſayings of the Lord our God in which he promiſeth to be the protector of his elect, &amp; to graunt them his ſauing helpe. <hi>Iſai 41.</hi> God ſaith, feare thou not, for I am with thee, be not afrayd, for I am thy God, I will ſtrengthen thee and help thee, and will ſuſtayne thee with the right hand of my iuſtice. The faithful man doth learne of
<hi>Dauid</hi> to ſaye <hi>Pſal. 28.</hi> The Lorde is my ſtrength and my ſhielde, my hart truſted in him &amp; I was helped, therfore myne hart ſhal reioyce, &amp; with my ſong wil I praiſe him. The faithfull doe ſaye as <hi>Pſal. 32.</hi> Our foule waiteth for the Lord, for he is our helpe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3119:46"/> and our ſhielde. And of the Prophet he lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, <hi>Pſal. 37.</hi> That the ſaluation of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous men ſhalbe of the Lord: he ſhalbe their ſtrength in the time of trouble. For the Lorde ſhal helpe them, and deliuer them, he ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them from the wicked, &amp; ſhall ſaue them becauſe they truſt in him. And they haue ſuch a corage &amp; faith in God his goodnes, might, and mercy, that they ſay <hi>Pſal. 23.</hi> Though I do walke through the valley of the ſhadowe of death, I will feare no euill, for thou art with me, thy rod and thy ſtaffe, they comforte me. And they ſaye alſo, <hi>Pſal. 48.</hi> This God is our God for euer and euer, he ſhalbe our guide vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the death. Thus doth the Lorde allure his people to looke for ſaluation and protection at his hande, and for his ſauing helpe in all their perills. And we reade that Chriſt our Sauior at his death cried out with a loude voyce, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into thy handes I commende my ſpirite <hi>Luc. 23.</hi> and by his example doth teache vs to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 7.</note> For God is our protector &amp; defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. <hi>Stephen</hi> alſo ſtoned to death cried, Lorde Ieſu receaue my ſpirite: to the Lord Ieſus as to his onely protector, he doth commende him ſelfe, and by his example he hath taught vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend our ſelues to this protector as he did, and therfore in Ieſus alone let vs reſt &amp; abide,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:3119:46"/> ſo ſhall we be moſt ſafely kept and protected, as the Pſalmiſt ſayth, <hi>Pſal. 91.</hi> Who ſo dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the ſecret of the moſt high, ſhal abide in the ſhadow of the Almighty. For truly he that maketh God his defence &amp; truſt ſhall perceaue his protection to be a moſt ſure ſafegard, as it is at large ſet foorth in that Pſalme, which I wiſhe the godly reader diligently to reade and marke, and he ſhall learne of
<hi>Dauid</hi> in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pſalter that God is his protector. But <hi>M. Fowler</hi> in this his Pſalter, or rather in this his fiddle, aſſigneth vs to an other protection then
<hi>Dauid</hi> doth in his Pſalter, whereby the reader may perceaue that theſe Pſalters doe not agree. We haue not learned to pray the Lord Ieſus by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merites of his glorious paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to graunt ſuch petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as <hi>M. Fowler</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth here: as that we ſhoulde offer our ſelues to the merits of Gods mother, and other holy Sainctes, and aſke their protection. The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of Ieſus Chriſt crucified for vs, are of ſuch a merite, that for our ſafety, protection, &amp; ſaluation, we neede no other merite either of the mother of God, or of any Sainct, but the onely merite of Ieſus Chriſt alone. The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of Ieſus Chriſt alone haue fully merited &amp; deſerued for vs which do truſt in him only, &amp; ſeeke at his hande only all our ſafety &amp; full ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:3119:47"/> He doth not ſend vs to ſeeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merites of his mother or of any other ſaincts. And this value and force of Chriſtes power &amp; merites <hi>M. Fowler</hi> him ſelfe ſemeth to haue found out once againe. For in his eleuenth petition, he prayeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord Ieſus thus: <hi>Thy power protect me, &amp; againe, thy paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſerue me from euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting damnation, and terror of mine enemy.</hi> In deede theſe wordes haue ſome good ſauor and ſound of truth, but he woulde neuer haue min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merites &amp; protection of Sainctes with the merites and protection of Chriſt, if he had hartily reaſted on the protection of Ieſus, and vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merites of the Lord Ieſus alone, for he ſhoulde haue founde him ſelfe ſo ſafe in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he woulde neuer haue ſought others as euen now he did. And here you may once againe marke a iarre, that <hi>Fowler</hi> in his Pſalter maketh not onely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> his Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but euen with him ſelfe alſo. We knowe that Ieſus Chriſt alone, is the ſufficient pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of his elect, they are all giuen vnto him of his father, none can take them out of his hand, he hath not ioyned with him in this pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tectinge power any other perſon, neither his mother nor Sainct. And therfore the ſheepe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord Ieſus doe greatly reioyce in this, that they may reſt protected &amp; conducted by Ieſus
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:3119:47"/> Chriſt alone, wherof the Pſalmiſt doth ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinge <hi>Pſal.
23.</hi> In the ſame eleauenth peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Fowler</hi> prayeth: <hi>That God woulde keepe his mouth from ſlaunderous speaking, lying, falſe witnes bearing, &amp;c.</hi> If this requeſt had bene graunted, <hi>Maiſter Fowler</hi> had made no ſuch Pſalter as he hath at this time, in which is much lying, falſe witnes bearing, and ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous ſpeaking, as in part you haue hearde and yet more ſhall heare by Gods grace. In the twelf petition he hath this: <hi>In my tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Lord I beſeech thee to helpe me, for the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der loue that thou diddeſt ſhew to thy mother &amp; she to thee.</hi> It is well that he prayeth the Lord Ieſus to helpe him in his temptations, but to require him to doe it for the loue that he did beare to his mother and ſhe to him, is a thinge farre featched. Why <hi>M. Fowler</hi> hath not the Lord Ieſus borne any loue to you your ſelfe, that is worth the remembring? We know that the Lorde Ieſus did tenderly loue his mother and ſhe him againe, but that loue which he doth beare to mankinde is no leſſe, and is alſo of his owne free goodnes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 15.</note> Of loue he did giue his life for his ſheepe, &amp; greater loue then this hath no man, when any man beſtoweth his life for his freindes. This is that great loue which Ieſus hath borne to vs, the Chriſtians
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:3119:48"/> which doe beleue in him &amp; harken to his voice. And the holy Ghoſt teacheth vs to learne, to vnderſtande and to taſte howe ſweete this loue is, wherewith the Lord God our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and our good Lord Ieſus haue loued vs, for that loue is our life. Of this loue the Lord Ieſus doth teach vs ſaying <hi>Ioan. 3.</hi> So God loued the worlde that he hath giuen his onely ſonne, that whoſoeuer beleueth in him ſhoulde not periſh but haue life euerlaſting. The ſame our louing Lorde Ieſus ſayth of this his loue towards vs
<hi>Ioan. 13.</hi> As the father hath loued me, ſo haue I loued you. And in his prayer <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.
17.</hi> he asketh thus. That the loue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou haſt loued me, may be in them, and I in them. Thus are we taught in the holy Scriptures to vnderſtande the loue of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the loue of the ſonne towards vs. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is there ſayd to teache vs to looke to the loue which his mother did beare to him. Yea he ſayth <hi>Ioan. 10.</hi> I am the good ſhepheard, the good ſhephearde giueth his life for his ſheepe. And againe, therefore doth my father loue me, becauſe I lay downe my life. And <hi>S. Iohn</hi> teacheth vs. Beholde what loue the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ſhewed on vs, that we ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſonnes of God. <hi>1. Ioan. 5.</hi> And againe he ſayth, In this appeared the loue of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3119:48"/> vs, becauſe he ſent his onely begotten ſonne into the world, that we might liue tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough him. Herein is loue, not that we loued God, but that he loued vs, and ſent his ſonne to be a reconciliation for our ſinnes. <hi>1. Ioan. 4.</hi> Thus doth the ſpirite of God lay forth that loue before vs in which lyeth our life. Of this loue <hi>S. Paule</hi> hauing a right good taſte wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Gal. 2. I liue</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>by the faith of the ſonne of God, who loued me and hath giuen him ſelfe for me.</hi> In this loue which Chriſt Ieſus beareth to vs, is the very life of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull, and therfore to it they muſt &amp; they do looke. As we reade <hi>Apoca. 1.</hi> vnto him that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs and waſhed vs from our ſinnes in his blood, &amp; made vs kinges &amp; prieſtes vnto God his father, vnto him be glory &amp; dominion for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore. Thus are we taught to taſte the loue wherewith Ieſus Chriſt hath loued vs our ſelues, howſoeuer either he loued his mother or ſhe loued him. In the thirteenth petition he hath put in this patche: <hi>Make me patiently to ſuffer iniuries and rebukes in recompenſe of my diſobedient hart to thee.</hi> To ſuffer iniuries and rebukes for Chriſtes ſake patiently, and for well doinge is a bleſſednes. And can not this ſuffice <hi>Maiſter Fowler?</hi> but he muſt alſo make his patience a recompenſe to God for
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:3119:49"/> the diſobedience of his hart? Of this his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipte of recompencing God for ſinne, I haue ſpoken before, and the leſſe ſhall I neede to ſpeake of it now, becauſe
<hi>M. Fowler</hi> him ſelfe alſo, euen in this ſame petition, belike miſdou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his owne recompencinge of God for his own ſinnes, doth flee to the recompence which the Lorde Ieſus hath made for vs, and ſayeth: <hi>Let thine obedience recompence for my obſtinacy, thine abſtinence for my ſuperfluity, thy meekenes and thy patience for my pride, irefull hart &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, thy charity for my malice, thy deuotion for my dulnes, thy louinge hart for my vnkindnes, thy holy death for my wretched life &amp; for all my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</hi> Theſe are the words of
<hi>M. Fowler</hi> in this ſame thirteenth petition, in which he doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Lord Ieſus to make the recompence for all his ſinnes and miſery. And what is it then wherefore he woulde him ſelfe make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence by his patience? He ſayeth for his diſobedient hart. But for this he prayeth the Lord Ieſus to make recompence. He ſeemeth in theſe wordes not to truſt to the value of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compencing by his owne patience, but pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the pacience of the Lord Ieſus may be a recompence for his owne pride, irefull hart, and enmity. You ſee nowe once againe how contrary <hi>M. Fowler</hi> is to himſelfe in this
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3119:49"/> petition, &amp; what a iarre this contrariety doth make in this his Pſalter. In deede the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence which he woulde him ſelfe make by his patience for the diſobedience of his own hart, is farre out of tune, and ſoundeth vnſauerily in the vnderſtandinge of any true chriſtian. But this recompence which he findeth that Ieſus hathe made for his elect, is a ſweete ſauour of life to the ſoules of true chriſtians, &amp; agreeth with the ſaying of the Prophet <hi>Iſai. 53.</hi> He ſet or made his life for a ſacrifice of ſinne. This recompence which Ieſus Chriſt hathe made, &amp; that which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> would himſelf make, can not be coupled together. For Ieſus alone and only made the iuſt and full recompence for the ſinnes of all them whiche are to be ſaued. In the laſt, that is, in the fifteenth petition <hi>M. Fowler</hi> addeth: <hi>This inuocation and Pſalter of thee by the mediation of thy moſt entirely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued mother purchaſe to me gratious life, &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ending, free from debte, and deadly ſinne I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, and after my bodily death euerlaſting life, with endleſſe bliſſe and felicity. <hi>M. Fowler</hi>
               </hi> muſt firſt proue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is the Pſalter of Ieſus before he can thus call and commend it, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute ſuch force vnto it, as he doth. And lette the reader marke how <hi>M. Fowler</hi> him ſelfe, as it were doubting of the value, vertue, or force
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:3119:50"/> of this his Pſalter, ioyneth to it, as a poore help to helpe it forwarde, the mediation of the bleſſed virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> For he woulde haue his Pſalter to be of valure to purchaſe for him, by the mediation of the bleſſed virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> Of her mediation we knowe nothinge as I haue ſaid before: we do truſt only to the mediatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of her moſt gracious ſonne our good Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who is the one, &amp; ſo the only Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene God and man. For we are taught by <hi>S. Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi>
2.</note> that there is one God and one Mediator betwene God &amp; man, euen the man Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. But <hi>M Fowler</hi> like a ſloue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>like apoticary mingleth this his Pſalter &amp; the mediation of the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> both together, to the ende be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, that if the one failed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other might ſerue the turne. And he prayeth that this his medly may purchaſe firſt gracious life. This tearme gracious which he vſeth, teacheth vs, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he meaneth by gracious life, that it is the worke of Gods free grace, and therefore commeth not by purchaſe either of this Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or of the mediation of the virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> He addeth that by this mingle he would purchaſe bleſſed endinge free from debte, and deadely ſinne. Touchinge the payment of his debtes, it may be that <hi>M. Fowler</hi> thinketh to prouide ſome poore helpe, by printing of this Pſalter,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3119:50"/> and that the good vent thereof may be a great helpe to him, if he be in debte. But it is harde dealing to get the money of true men for falſe ware. It is more hard to lay ſuch ſnares of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit to intrappe the ſimple ſoules of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as <hi>M. Fowler</hi> doth, for getting of money to paye his debtes. Whatſoeuer <hi>M. Fowler</hi> dreameth of payment of his debtes, we knowe the payment and ſatisfaction for al our ſinnes is the price which Ieſus Chriſt payed in his moſt pretious bitter and bloody death ſuffred on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe for vs. That onely maketh vs free, other freedom purchaſed either by this Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or by the mediation of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or any other way which <hi>M. Fowler</hi> and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes can deuiſe, we know none, we wil none. We doe by Gods grace knowe that freedome into which we are called by Ieſus Chriſt, who as he onely coulde, ſo he hath moſt gratiouſly made vs free. In that fredom by his grace we doe and ſhall ſtand. By this mingle <hi>M. Fowler</hi> would purchaſe alſo life euerlaſting. He thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth but ſimply and baſely of life euerlaſting, which doth thinke that it may be purchaſed by ſuch a filthy fiddle as is this Pſalter, or by ſuch a mingle mangle as <hi>Fowler</hi> maketh. But we haue learned and doe beleue that life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting is (as I ſayd before) the gifte of God
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:3119:51"/> thorough Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde. It is his gifte, it is not by this Pſalter, nor by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> to be purchaſed. We doe giue vnto God the glorie and prayſe due, of, and for the gifte of life euerlaſtinge by Ieſus Chriſt. We will not ſeeke it by any other meanes, nor goe about to purchaſe that our ſelues, which is thus gratiouſly and freely giuen vnto vs. Thus endeth this Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (ſayth <hi>Maiſter Fowler</hi>) and yet he addeth an <hi>admonition,</hi> a poynt of holſom doctrine be ye ſure, and a <hi>Narration</hi> of nothing verely in effect, yet be they ſolemnly added to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe vppe the trayne of this his Pſalter. But <hi>Maiſter Fowler</hi> wanteth one thinge vſuall in ſuch preatty popiſhe deuiſes. That is ſome Bull to be graunted by his moſt holy father Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> that nowe is, of pardon for ſuch as ſhal deuoutly ſay this Pſalter. Popes were wont to be liberall to beawtifie ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptes with large pardons for thowſandes of yeares. <hi>Maiſter Fovvler</hi> was much ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene that he did not ſue to Rome for ſuche a pardon to haue annexed it to his Pſalter. Such a <hi>Bull</hi> woulde haue gotten eaſie ſale of his Pſalter amonge the Romiſhe <hi>Calues,</hi> and ſo haue made well for the payment of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Fovvlers</hi> debtes. And we may thinke
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:3119:51"/> that <hi>Maiſter Fovvler</hi> might haue come in a very ſeaſonable tyme to his father Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> on this meſſage. For it doth appeare that this Pope was ſo full of his popiſh grace about the tyme of the publiſhing of this Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that at an eaſie entreatie of <hi>Maiſter Inglefeilde,</hi> and one <hi>Maiſter Allen</hi> he did li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally graunt pardon and pardon againe to ſuch as ſhall haue but one of the beade ſtones which he hath bleſſed. What would not this Pope then haue graunted vpon ſmall entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to him that ſhould haue had, and ſayd this <hi>Pſalter of Fowler?</hi> But if it were ſo that this <hi>Pſalter</hi> was offred to the Pope to be bleſſed &amp; dubbed with a pardon, &amp; he refuſed ſo to doe, &amp; yet he hath ſo plentifully beſtowed his bleſſing vpon a poore beadſtone, ſurely it is ynough to marre <hi>M. Fowlers</hi> markett. For then euery man will thinke that Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> did not eſteeme ſo much of <hi>Maiſter Fowlers</hi> Pſalter as he did of a ſimple beadeſtone. A thinge of ſmall price and value ſurely, not vnlike to the value of the Popes bleſſing beſtowed on it, that is of no valure at all. But if a bleſſed beadeſtone may bringe by the popes <hi>Bull</hi> full remiſſion of all ſinnes, as his blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Bull</hi> importeth: Then lette <hi>Maiſter Fovvler</hi> goe hange vppe his pſalter vppon
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:3119:52"/> ſome pynne on the wall, for it can profitte no other man, nor yet him ſelfe any waye that I knowe. If Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> that nowe is woulde haue done ſo much for this Pſalter of <hi>Maiſter Fowler</hi> as Pope <hi>Pius</hi> did for his own primer, it might haue ſerued much better <hi>M. Fovvlers</hi> turne then nowe it can, For Pope <hi>Pius</hi> doth ſolemnly reuoke and put out of vſe all other primers, to make place for his owne Primer nowe printed by <hi>Plantine</hi> at And<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warpe, and alſo giueth preattie pardons to them which ſhall vſe it. If Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> had bene ſo good a fellow to prouide for <hi>Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> pſalter, that is, if he had adnihilated and put out of vſe all other pſalters, and then dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed this pſalter of <hi>Fowlers</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a pardon, what had <hi>M. Fowler</hi> I pray you then wanted? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing verely but truth. It may be that <hi>Maiſter Fowler</hi> thought that the romiſh popes had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready dealt forth their bleſſed graces in their pardons ſo plentifully for many thowſandes of yeares yet to come, that nowe they had no more ſtoare of ſuche graces lefte them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow by pardons. So might it alſo haue bene thought that the Romiſhe ſeduced ſect had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready gotten ſuch ſtoare of pardoned yeares for ages to come, and by pardons ſuch full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all their ſinnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they neded not now
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:3119:52"/> to care for any more newpardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. But in error there is no ſtay. I wil leaue therfore <hi>M. Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> to ſue at <hi>Rome,</hi> if he be ſo fooliſh, for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to furniſh this his fiddle which he calleth a Pſalter. But I do wiſh rather to <hi>M. Fowler</hi> with all my hart that true chriſtian vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which may ſhew him his error, &amp; grace to forſake it, &amp; to embrace the trueth of Chriſt Ieſus our Sauiour, as it is taught and ſette forth in the word of truth, the moſt holy word of God, I meane. Here I woulde ende as he endeth his Pſalter, ſauing that I thinke good in concludinge to anſwere an obiection which may be made to me. It may be ſayed, that I haue not touched all his whole Pſalter, but haue left much not ſpoken of, which is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in it. It is true, I haue only touched ſome ſuch ſtringes as doe make a fowle iarre from the ſoundnes of our chriſtian faith &amp; of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures. And yet I haue not touched all but left ſome vntouched, ſuppoſinge that this which I haue wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may giue the godly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſufficient warning of all the reſt. This li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leauen which I haue touched, ſowreth his whole pſalter, and maketh it vnſauery to him that taſteth how ſweete y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord is in his truth and mercy. But he will ſay that <hi>Fowler</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth alſo ſome good wordes in his Pſalter.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:3119:53"/> What thereof? The deuil him ſelfe ſometime ſpeaketh truth, but he is to be put to ſilence. For his purpoſe is by vttering ſome truth to get credit to be beleued in his falſhoode.<note place="margin">Hieron. in Ierem. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> We are forewarned by an old writer, that falſhood doth imitate truth alwayes, and that vnles it haue ſome likelihoode of trueth it can not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue. So it may be that <hi>M. Fowler</hi> ſpeaketh of purpoſe in ſome pointes of his pſalter a truth, but vnder that we muſt take heede that he creepe not into ſuch creditte with vs, that therefore we ſhoulde receaue as truth all that he printeth, for then you ſee what ſtincking filth we ſhall receaue. It is a manner of foy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to ſette forth their falſhoodes with ſome ſhew of truth, elſe ſhould they lay them ſelues to open, and marre their owne market. It is the duetie of all them which will praye well, and acceptably vnto God, to make thoſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which are ſound and wholy agreeing with Gods moſte holy will witneſſed in his holy word. Let men take heede of offering ſtraung fier to God, I meane that they doe not make ſtraunge prayers to God, for if they do, they ſhall feele the paines thereof and ſuffer bitter reiection. Let vs learne to pray to God him ſelfe, ſithence he doth vouchſafe to become our Scholemaiſter herein, and doth teach vs how
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3119:53"/> to pray in his ſight acceptably, &amp; to our ſelues moſt profitably. If we do deſpiſe ſuch a ſchole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter, if we will refuſe his teaching, and wil be teachers to our ſelues, and thruſt vpon him our owne deuiſes, we doe ſhew our ſelues to be ſtubborne and proud rebells, he will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept vs, but reiect vs, the loſſe and paine ſhall be ours. It had bene the part of <hi>M. Fovvler</hi> to haue learned of Ieſus our Lord and moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Sauiour how to pray, and then woulde he not haue preſumed thus to packe vp this <hi>peeuish Pſalter,</hi> and to ſet it on vent vnder the bleſſed name of
<hi>Ieſus.</hi> This is a boldnes intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable.<note place="margin">To. <hi>2.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cil. cap. Grec. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod.</note> I reade that there were ſome pſalmes or himnes deuiſed by men which were forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to be vſed of Chriſtians in the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that by the conſent of ſome Elders ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in councell. Mention is made alſo in <hi>Euſebius</hi> how ſome hereticks had their new pſalmes of their owne. Such a pſalter is this, and ſuche pſalmes here hath <hi>M. Fovvler</hi> made, if not worſe then they were, as worthy to be forbidden as they, and to be auoyded of al true Chriſtians, who are as I ſaid to learne of the Lord him ſelf how to offer this ſacrifice of prayer to him: and it is our duetie both to thanke him that it hath pleaſed him to become our teacher, and alſo to ſuffer our ſelues to be
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3119:54"/> taught of him, yea and to harken to that which is ſayd, and by the ſpirit of God taught vs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Coloſſ. 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Let the vvord of Chriſt dvvell in you plenteouſly in all vviſedom, teaching and admonishing your ovvne ſelues in pſalmes and himnes and ſpirituall ſonges, ſinging vvith grace in your hartes vnto the Lord, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>Prayſe God. TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Owler addeth vnto his fiddle whiche he calleth a Pſalter, an admonition. It may (I truſt) be as lawefull for me, nowe in the ende of this booke to adde a few words in way of a neceſſary admonition. VVhen the Pope sheweth himſelfe liberal in giuinge of Pardons to them which will pray ſo as he appointeth them, &amp; when papiſts are buſie to make vs Pſalters and ſuch prety in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentes whereon to pray, a man woulde
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3119:54"/> thinke that both he &amp; they were become ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deuoute. But euen theſe very ſame men, when this word prayer is moſt buſie in their mouthes, haue in their hartes &amp; hands fowle &amp; bloody practiſes, to cut the throates of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom they doe allure to pray with them. In which they do not ſo cloſely work, but God of his goodnes, doth diſcouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bleſſed be his name for it. He doth bevvray vnto vs that blood thriſt vvhich lieth in their hartes. For, they do in dede ſecretly labor &amp; practiſe the sheding of our blood &amp; the murthering of vs all, whileſt they doe allure vs to pray, as they preſcribe vs. And therfore iuſt cauſe we haue novve to complaine on theſe enemies as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid doth vppon his:
<hi>Pſal. 55. The wordes of his mouth were ſofter then butter, yet warre was in his hart: His words were more gentle then oyle, yet they were ſwords.</hi> VVe may likevviſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine as he doth, <hi>Pſal. 120. My ſoule hath to longe dwelt with him that hateth peace. I ſeeke peace, &amp; when I ſpeake thereof, they are bent to warre.</hi> In theſe practiſes of the ſeede of Cain, that is of theſe romish catholikes (for ſo they vvil be called) vve do ſe that fulfilled vvhich vvas foretold vs by our Sauior Chriſt. <hi>Ioh. 16. That whoſoeuer killeth you, will thinke that he doth God ſeruice.</hi> Thus are the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3119:55"/> forevvarned that they shall finde enemies ſo deuout &amp; cruell, that they shall thinke them ſelues to do good and acceptable ſacrifice to God in ſlaying &amp; killing of them. This is an opinion vvhich is putte into their mindes by the deuill that old murtherer &amp; liar: &amp; in this murthering, the murtherers do this their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to the deuil him ſelfe. The old perſequu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge Pagans thus ſerued their Gods, that is, the deuill him ſelfe in bloody ſlayinges and murtheringes of Chriſtians. In deede it is the delight of the deuil to ſmell the ſauor of ſuch ſacrifices. And therfore euen among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans and Idolaters, the deuill that olde mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer hadde ſovved this deluſion, that they vvere induced to thinke it to be a moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſeruice to their Idolls, to offer vnto them men, vvomen, &amp; children in ſlaine ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice like beaſts. Yea ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did doate herein ſo egregiouſly, that they ſpared not their ovvne ſonnes, and daughters, but made vnnaturall ſlaughters of their naturall chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the deuil him ſelfe in their Idols. And this vvas amonge them a thinge ſo common and horrible,<note place="margin">Cl. Alex.</note> that euen of this their cruell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity did ſome olde doctors and vvry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Chriſtes church gather argumentes to proue thoſe Idols falſe deuils and their vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:3119:55"/> Idolatry, and to dravv thoſe Idolaters from their barbarous infidelitie to the faith of Chriſt. The ſame pagans alſo vvere taught by the deuill their ſchoolemaiſter to thinke ſometime that it vvas meete for them to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie their gods, and to procure them ſelues felicity by makinge of hauocke and cruell ſlaughters of the godly olde Chriſtians. The ſame murtherer the deuill vvhich vvrought theſe miſchiefes then, doth vſe ſtill his olde pranckes, and doth ſturre vp papiſtes novv to practiſe the like inhumaine &amp; cruell ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vpon the poore flock &amp; sheepe of Chriſt, as he did by Pagans then. They thinke it an acceptable ſeruice &amp; ſacrifice to their God. But it is only a pleaſing ſeruice to the deuill of hel, and the deuill it is vvhom papiſtes do ſerue herein. They thinke by theſe meanes to extinguish the faith, the religion, &amp; true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſt, that their popish Idols may keepe the place of God, and be counted and vvorshipped as God only and alone vppon earth, vvherein they ſerue the deuill himſelfe to the vttermoſt of their povver. Many are the vnnaturall ſlaughters vvhich not onelie before vs, but euen in our age papiſtes haue made in Fraunce, at Merindoll, Paris, and through that vvhole realme, in Flaunders al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:3119:56"/> and Spayne, England and elſe vvhere as the hiſtories of our age doe beare teſtimony. But if that God vvhom Papiſts vvorship be ſuch a cruel belly god, that he is beſt pleaſed vvhen men are ſlayne for his pleaſure, vve may ſafely ſay then that, that vvhich the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts doe vvorshippe vvith ſuch ſeruice, is the very deuill of hell. For the Lord God the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of heauen and earth, God the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the onely true liuing God, accepteth no ſuch ſeruice, no ſuch ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and he vvill in his appoynted time call theſe butchers and men quellers to as feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full an accompte for theſe their cruell doings as once he called Cain for the ſlaughter of his brother Abell. Yea let them proceede, they shall but fill vppe the meaſure of their ſinnes, that vpon them (as Chriſt ſayth) may come all the righteous blood that vvas shed vpon the earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.</note> from the blood of Abell the righteous, vnto the blood of Zacharias the ſonne of Barachias, &amp;c. But you vvill ſay theſe men be deuoute in their prayers. They doe pray: ſo did Cain: ſo did Doeg, make a ſemblance of praying and ſacrificing, but this vvas but the counterfetting of theſe caſt-avvayes. And the Papiſts do think that vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt they do thus nourish this vnſatiable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3119:56"/> and deuiſe of theſe bloody maſſacres in their heartes, yet that they doe pray ſo vvell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, that they may allure others to pray vvith them. But in theſe their thoughtes they do erre, and are deceaued. For the Lord him ſelfe ſayeth by the Prophet.
<hi>Iſai. 1. VVhen you ſhall ſtretch out your hands I will hide mine eyes from you, and though you make many prayers, I will not heare, for your hands are full of blood.</hi> The prayers therfore of theſe bloody papiſts are not hearde, thankes be to God for it. But let vs al vvhich do profeſſe the religion of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt in truth, be admonished vvith care and diligence to practiſe right prayer accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God by Ieſus Chriſt our Sauior, and not forget that vvhileſt vve do pray, papiſtes haue ſtill their ſecrete practiſes to cut all our throates, and therefore let vs be prepared for them.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 72.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He shall redeeme their ſoules from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite, &amp; violence, &amp; deere shal their blood be in his ſight.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
